<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The conviction of James Naylor and his black spirit demonstrated from his own confessions, lyes, evasions, and contradictions in the maine points of doctrine by him held forth against the truth in answer to a book of his called Wickednesse weighed : the which was writt in answer to a little treatise called The Quakers quaking principles examined and refuted, written by Ellis Bradshavv ... / written by Ellis Bradshavve.</title>
            <author>Bradshaw, Ellis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29128</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37455</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16959073</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16959073</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105464</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29128)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105464)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1610:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The conviction of James Naylor and his black spirit demonstrated from his own confessions, lyes, evasions, and contradictions in the maine points of doctrine by him held forth against the truth in answer to a book of his called Wickednesse weighed : the which was writt in answer to a little treatise called The Quakers quaking principles examined and refuted, written by Ellis Bradshavv ... / written by Ellis Bradshavve.</title>
                  <author>Bradshaw, Ellis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for Lodowike Lloyd ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660. --  Wickedness weighed.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105464:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CONVICTION Of <hi>JAMES NAYLOR,</hi> and his black ſpirit, demonſtrated from his own confeſſions, lyes, evaſions and <hi>contradictions in the maine points of Doctrine by him held forth againſt the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to a Book of his called <hi>Wickedneſſe weighed.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>The which was writt in anſwer to a little Treatiſe called <hi>The Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers quaking Principles examined and Refuted,</hi> written by ELLIS BRADSHAVV.</item>
               <item>This Treatiſe is therefore directed by way of appeale to all the truly Judicious, to be weighed in the Ballance of the Sanctuary, and to ſee in which end of the ſcales the wickednes lyeth, his end or mine.</item>
               <item>And alſo ſome Rules held forth whereby to try the ſpirits, whether they be of God yea or no, in caſe of viſions or apparitions, yea dreames, or voyces, whether ſpeaking within or without.</item>
               <item>As alſo ſome Scripture Rules for diſcerning the motions and luſtings of the ſpirit and fleſh, each from the other, that ſo wee might not be led blind-fold to deſtruction by any deluding ſpirits within us or without.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Written by ELLIS BRADSHAVVE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts 13.9, 10, 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Then Saul who alſo is called Paul, filled with the holy Ghoſt, ſett his eyes on him, And ſaid, Oh full of all ſubtiltie and all miſchiefe, thou child of the Devill, thou enemy of all goodneſſe, how long wilt thou not ceaſe to pervert the right wayes of the Lord; And now behold the hand of the Lord is upon thee, and thou ſhalt be blind, not ſeeing the Sunne for a ſeaſon. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Lodowike Lloyd,</hi> at the Caſtle in <hi>Cornwall.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105464:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105464:2"/>
            <head>THE CONVICTION of <hi>JAMES NAYLOR,</hi> and his black ſpirit, demonſtrated from his own confeſſions, lyes, evaſions and <hi>contradictions in the maine points of Doctrine by him held forth againſt the truth.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EADERS; <hi>James Naylor</hi> aſſerteth in his Title page concerning my booke that it is dedicated as (I ſay) unto his Highneſſe the Lord Protector, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The which I ſay is true; but what of that? he ſaith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and therefore needeth no anſwer.</p>
            <p>But further he ſaith, that it is much boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted off by the Author, but as little worth, as the boaſt is great.</p>
            <p>I anſwer; I did commend it to ingage his Highnes to the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, leaſt his multitude of buiſineſſe ſhould cauſe him to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect it. And what of all that? doth not <hi>James Naylor</hi> commend his Doctrines, and Teachings, and Judgements, and Cenſures, and tells us it is by the eternall light and Spirit of God that he holdeth them forth, as you may ſee in any of his Bookes: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we know he lyeth; But it will appeare, I therein ſpeake the truth, and nothing more.</p>
            <p>And as for the worth of that Treatiſe when it is weighed in the Ballance of the Sanctuary, it will appeare I did not over-value it in my commendations of it, but of that let the readers judge.</p>
            <p>Againe, he ſaith alſo; that it was my envie that carried mee with ſuch envie againſt the innocent, till I ſpake I knew not what
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105464:3"/>concerning the Father, and the Sonne, the Word, the Light, and Spirit.</p>
            <p>I anſwer; though he Judge ſo of me, whom in deriſion he calleth (the man) yet the truth is, I care not to be Judged of <hi>James Naylor,</hi> Nor for ought he knoweth not of mans Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; But he that Judgeth me is the Lord; Nor would I change my condition with <hi>James Naylor.</hi> nor for ought he knoweth not with any man living on the earth. And how then can <hi>James Naylor</hi> know that it was envie that carried me: And how can I envie thoſe I account off to be wicked and deſtinate to deſtruction for ought I yet ſee in them, that in my apprehenſion are farre from innocency in the ſight of God. And how dare I then <hi>be envious againſt them, or chooſe any of their wayes;</hi> ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37 1. &amp; <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.1. I ſhall not envie them till they be more innocent, then I yet ſee them. And therefore his cenſure of mee that I ſpeake I know not what, doth not trouble mee at all; for I expected no better f om his lying ſpirit. Though he cannot nor doth not in the leaſt prove it ſo in any of his Anſwers; And why ſhould I beleeve it upon his owne teſtimony, who beginneth with lyes in his Title page. Againe hee ſaith, That here is alſo ſome markes and maintenance of the true Miniſters ſet downe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the falſe, their fruits differing them, accoring to Chriſts Rules in Scripture, with diverſe other things to keepe the ſimple from deceite. All which when weighed in the ballance, let the truth appeare, for ſo I wiſh of God, whether they be or no true or falſe, according to Chriſts Rule in Scripture: yea whether they be in deed to keepe the ſimple from deceite; or clearely and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>to deceive the ſimple,</hi> and to make them alſo deceivers of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And againe, he telleth us it is by a friend to the worke of God, but an enemy to the Devills worke where it is found and pleaded for, called of the world <hi>James Naylor.</hi> To this I anſwer, that if this were true, what then ſhould be the reaſon that hee blameth me in his ſecond page for asking Why ſhould not I <hi>whiles I am in the world</hi> endeavour <hi>to deſtroy the works of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi> ſeeing he ſayth of himſelfe that he is an enemy to the worke of the Devill; and if he be ſo, he will labour to deſtroy it; for it is doubtleſſe lawfull and a following of Chriſt as much as in us lyeth, <hi>to deſtroy the works of the Devill;</hi> and none but Devills and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105464:3"/>their inſtruments will blame any man for ſo indeavouring, nor call it a ſetting of himſelfe to the ſtead of Chriſt; for no man can ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe it or indeavour it, what in him lyeth, but through his grace and aſſiſtance, and the power of his Spirit; as ſo I never ſpake otherwiſe in all my life. And he can and will for ought <hi>Naylor</hi> knoweth, enable mee in ſome meaſure by his ſtrength to doe it. But if I be an exilted wretch, and ſeeke to ſet my ſelfe in the ſtead of Chriſt, as ſo he calleth mee; I know he will not, and therefore it is in vaine to indeavour it; for <hi>hee giveth his grace to the humble. And beholdeth the wicked as a farre off;</hi> and as having no mind to Imploy them in any ſuch ſervice, nor any ſuch as are ſetled in their wickedneſſe, and dare take the office of Chriſt, and attribute it to themſelves; But the <hi>Quakers</hi> looke for ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves they are eaſily found; And it is the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſpirit, and not the Spirit of God, that ever did or ſhall puffe men up to any ſuch conceits or apprehenſion of themſelves; And what <hi>James Naylor</hi> may conceite of himſelfe I well know not.</p>
            <p>For ſomething or other hee would intimate unto us when hee putteth that preamble before his name, as in many of his Bookes, to wit, <hi>Called of the world James Naylor.</hi> Now whether hee would have us thinke that hee is the Chriſt the ſonne of the living God; and that Chriſt that dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was but a type of him; as their brother <hi>John Toldervie</hi> was perſwaded by their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit but was deceived; I ſhall not Judge: Or whether hee would Intimate to us that his Name was changed when he was conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and called as <hi>Paul</hi> (by an Immediate voyce of Chriſt, or his Angel <hi>Michael</hi> at leaſt, who is his Repreſentative) And that to the Miniſterie; as ſo hee writeth of himſelfe that he was called to the Miniſterie by an Immed are voyce: I ſhall not determine, nor doe I much care.</p>
            <p>But if his name was changed, I know no reaſon why he ſhould conceale it, but might make it knowne, as <hi>Paul</hi> alſo did his; ſo that many of the world know how <hi>Paul</hi> was called. But it may be <hi>James Naylor</hi> is loath to declare it, leaſt he ſhould declare the true ſignification of his name to others; not knowing it himſelfe; for it may be ſome great Schollers that are better learned then he; in that kinde of learning, would diſcover him by it, and for who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſervice he was intended, and ſo obſtruct his worke who is his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105464:4"/>Maſter; For if he ſhould be knowne properly by his name, hee might poſſibly be thereby knowne whoſe ſervant he is: For we reade of a kinde of Locuſts, <hi>Revel.</hi> 10th, a ſtrange kinde of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; who yet had a <hi>King over them, who is the Angel of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe pit, whoſe name in the Hebrew tongue is Abaddon, but in the Greeke tongue his name is Apollyon:</hi> Which is to ſay, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer, ſee <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. And ſo we reade their buſineſſe was no better. Now if his new name being interpreted ſhould diſcover him to be one of theſe Locuſts, he might well be avoyded that he could not deſtroy according to his end, and name, and nature. And therefore it is his pollicie in all likelihood to keepe it ſecret. Now it is evident for all his cloſeneſſe and pollicie to hide his deſigne, that if it lyeth in his power, or the ſpirit that acteth him, that all the Miniſters in the world that allow not his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, nor follow his wayes, but preach in our old publike meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing places, which hee calleth Idoll-Temples, and the people alſo that heare and maintaine them muſt all be deſtroyed and come to naught, and that in a ſhort time, elſe his ſpirit deceiveth him; yet wee feare not his Propheſies if hee and ſuch Locuſts will but hould their hands; for wee have a promiſe they ſhall onely hurt thoſe men that have not the ſeale of God upon their foreheads: Yet doe but ſpiritually paralell the caſe of theſe people with thoſe Locuſts there ſpoken off, and you will certainly conclude, there was never any ſo like them ſince the <hi>Revelation</hi> was given forth that we can reade of in Hiſtories. But the paralells would ſwell this Treatiſe to a great volume: And to produce any para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lells in oppoſition unto them is but accounted with them as a vaine piece of worke, and not worth anſwering, as I finde by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; For not one paralell that ever I produced againſt <hi>James Naylor</hi> is anſwered by him, but he ſlights them as not worth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering, or taking notice off. As for inſtance in this laſt Treatiſe I propoſed <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23. to wit, the <hi>fruit of the Spirit, is love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith, meekneſſe, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, againſt which there is no law.</hi> Upon which I tould them that I ſaw not ſo much as a ſhew of any of theſe in them, but the quite contrary, to wit, hatred, ſadneſſe of ſpirit and countenance, no peace with any man, no long-ſuffering, but haſtie rage, no gentleneſſe, but ſevere auſteritie, and imperious bitternes; no
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105464:4"/>goodneſſe, but cleare malignitie againſt all goodneſſe, no faith in God, but in a lying ſpirit within them, whom they obey and ſerve and worſhip as God, no meekneſſe, for they are haſtie, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, and revengefull; no temperance in their tongues and pens. And therefore every Law of God is againſt them; ſee this in <hi>page</hi> 59.</p>
            <p>But this he doth not anſwer at all, but when he hath made a Catalogue of ſuch things as he calleth lyes in my booke, he ſaith, Many more ſuch might be gathered out of this little Treatiſe (confeſſing) it hath much in it of ſuch ſtuffe, fit for the fire, yet he warneth mee that I ſhall not conclude that he owned the Reſt which he did not mention; ſaying that many more untruths are in my booke, not worth naming, nor anſwering: So that this I ſuppoſe is one that he meant; But I rather beleeve that hee durſt not mention them, having no ground at all for contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them. And leaſt it ſhould be a meanes to undeceive the ſimple, and let them ſee themſelves, and at what a great diſtance that ſpirit in them is from the ſpirit of God; which are beſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by their different fruits; And few of the <hi>Quakers</hi> but they buy his bookes, though they regard not others; for the moſt of his bookes are bought up by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and ſo take the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes as he repreſents it, as though there were nothing valuable in any againſt them but what he ſpecifieth, and ſo he deludeth the poore ſimple ſoules, and keepeth them blind, Reciting part of a ſentence, and concealing the Reſt, to make it untrue to their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, like a Jugling Cheater; as ſo he hath done in ſome parts of this his anſwer, which I hope to diſcover, and his Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious baſenes in that reſpect, to render mee a lyar and deceiver, and ſott, &amp;c. As ſo he calleth me without any reall or rationall cauſe, like his blacke father.</p>
            <p>And againe in his title page he citeth a Scripture, which being paraleld with their blaſphemous practiſes, includeth themſelves as copartners with the <hi>beaſt that had ſeaven heads, and ten hornes,</hi> that had upon <hi>his heads the names of blaſphemy, and opened his mouth in blaſphemies againſt God, to blaſpheme his Name, and his Tabernable, and them that dwell in heaven:</hi> All which he doth both by word and writing as is clearely proved in my little Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe; And yet he bringeth this Scripture, as ſomething applicable
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105464:5"/>to us: oh ſubtill Serpent! this is the old Serpents policie, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that to others which he feareth will be brought and applyed to himſelfe: and this he frequently uſeth in his bookes to bring ſuch Scriptures as his very Conſcience cannot chooſe but tell him are properly applicable againſt himſelfe, yet he bringth them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt others; that he may prevent them, by giving them firſt; and then he commonly putteth ſome cloud, or gloſſe upon them, meerely ſophiſticall.</p>
            <p>Againe in the Fronteſpice of his anſwer, he calleth me Friend, which when I began to conſider, what he meant by it in regard that ſpirit by which he is acted, ſeldome uſeth any ſuch loving appellations to its oppoſites; I wondered having not to my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance found the like in all his writings: But conſidering his words before and after to have nothing like any love in them, I was ſatisfied that he meant it no otherwiſe but as Chriſt did to <hi>Judas,</hi> who was going to betray him with a kiſſe, yet I thought it not proper to mee in regard I am not going to betray him, nor did not intend it in my Treatiſe, but onely to diſcover him and his falſe doctrines, and pernicious wayes, nor did offer him either a kiſſe or any thing elſe that ſhewed any love or reſpect to his wayes. And therefore in this ſence I diſowne it, and if hee meane it otherwiſe, the Reſt of his booke maketh it a lye.</p>
            <p>For then he beginneth in his old manner, and telleth mee how I boaſt of my booke, and what honour I ſeeke in owning what hath been done allready againſt a poore deſpiſed ſcorned help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe people, and that there is a lamentation for us, eſpecially though wee ſee it not, and that wee will ſee it in the end, and telleth us this is not the way to honour, againſt whom we are joyning, yet ſome of us will not be warned.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that I did commend my Treatiſe, but not my ſelfe, and that to ingage the reading of it; And as for ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of honour to my ſelfe, I am not conſcious to my ſelfe of any ſuch thing, and know by that <hi>James Naylor</hi> is guided by a lying ſpirit, which is not of God, for the Spirit of God would never have taught him any ſuch falſe furmiſes and ſuch abſolute lyes. Wherein he goeth on, telling mee that I ſaid in my laſt the Spirit of God taught mee to <hi>let other men praiſe me, and not my owne mouth, ſtrangers and not my owne lipps:</hi> but, ſaith he, thou haſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105464:5"/>forgot that teaching or rather never knew it; to which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer;</p>
            <p>That my words are theſe, to wit, that through the grace of God here are diverſe arguments and doctrines for provoking to good works, which have never yet that I know off been publiſhed before, either by word or writing from Goſpel foundations, but in this Treatiſe</p>
            <p>And this I affirme againe, that it is a truth, let <hi>James Naylor</hi> or any man elſe, produce any thing to the contrary if they can.</p>
            <p>But this is all nothing in commendations, or praiſing of my ſelfe, but of the Treatiſe onely, and that not as mine but through the grace of God, and therefore this may be ſett amongſt the Reſt of his manifeſt lyes.</p>
            <p>Againe, ſaith he, in thy booke there is foure things which thou wouldeſt ſtand for and proove if thou couldeſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the Letter is the Word.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Againſt the light of Chriſt being ſufficient.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, A large maintenance for thoſe thou calls Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Creature-Worſhips, and nationall cuſtomes, thou would binde us too.</p>
            <p>To the firſt I anſwer as I did then, that if he meane by the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any part of Scripture, I did aſſert and doe ſo againe, and did prove it to be the word of God, as ſo if he meane it as he hath printed his anſwer; for page 3. he ſaith, that I goe on to prove that there are many words of God, and that what God hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken is his word, and what Chriſt hath ſpoken is the word of God, and that the Scriptures given by inſpiration of God are words of God, and that <hi>every word of God is pure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which he ſaith are things never by <hi>James Naylor</hi> denyed.</p>
            <p>Now hee having confeſſed too all theſe aſſertions; firſt, that there are many words of God, and that what God hath ſpoken is his word, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet immediately after contradicting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he ſaith; And yet I ſay the word is but one, which is the word whether ſpoken or not ſpoken.</p>
            <p>If this be not a cleare contradiction, to confeſſe firſt that there are many words of God, and that all Scripture given by inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God are words of God; and yet deny that there is any word of God but one; Sure he imagineth that none but ſimple
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105464:6"/>deluded <hi>Quakers</hi> will reade his aſſertions, who thinking him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, can beleeve any thing that he aſſerteth; as Papiſts doe the Pope.</p>
            <p>For ſuppoſe one ſhould aske him whether the word he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of is God, yea or no, I ſuppoſe he would anſwer (yea) he is God; for Chriſt is the Word, and Chriſt is God.</p>
            <p>Now he hath confeſſed that there are many words of God, and ſuch as are ſo called in Scripture</p>
            <p>But is every word in Scripture that is called the word of God, and that properly, becauſe God hath ſpoken it, I ſay, is it God, becauſe it is the word of God. How many Gods would <hi>James Naylor</hi> reckon, for many words of God he hath owned, and if every ſuch word of God is God, there muſt needs be more Gods then one, though <hi>with us there is no God but one;</hi> nor did we ever ſay that the Scripture is God, but the words and word of God, and that he here confeſſeth, that all Scripture given by inſpiration of God is the words and word of God; as is proved in my Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, and here confeſſed by him. But if all Scriptures are the words of God, and yet he affirmeth the word is but one, and that word is Chriſt; Then by his Logicke it muſt needs follow, that there is no Chriſt but the Scriptures; nor any God but the Scriptures; nor any word of God but the Scriptures; and ſo hee denyeth the eternall eſſentiall word, which is Chriſt, or elſe maketh the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be hee, and ſo confoundeth himſelfe, and his maine aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to wit, that the Scripture is not the word of God; againſt which aſſertion is all our quarrell; For we doe not nor never did deny that Chriſt onely is the eſſentiall word, and not the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and this eſſentiall word is God, yet we ſay as ſo he confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that the Scripture is alſo the word of God, and is properly ſo called in Scripture, in regard it is ſpoken by his inſpiration. And that it is not blaſphemy to call the Scripture the word of God, but the blaſphemy is theirs that ſo aſſert. Nor can all his wicked evaſions helpe him to evade the dint of theſe arguments As when he further ſaith, that a man may have all the letter either in his hand, or in his braine, and yet have not the word.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, ſuppoſe wee graunt it that a man may have all the Scripture in his hand, and yet not have Chriſt, which is the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall word, yet he cannot have the Bible in his hand, but he hath
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105464:6"/>the Scripture, and that Scripture is the expreſſe word of God, and properly ſo called, and that in Scripture; and this is confeſſed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by him for there is no writings which wee call Scriptures, but in the Bible, and all thoſe Scriptures are given by inſpiration of God, and all Scriptures that are given by inſpiration of God, he hath acknowledged to be the words of God, and it is not proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called Scripture, that is not written. And <hi>that which was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten aforetime, was written for our learning, that wee through pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and comfort of the Scriptures might have hope:</hi> And woe unto ſuch as cannot finde comfort in them for ſtrengthning of their hope; for there is little hope of ſuch men, but how much leſſe hope is there of ſuch who are at enmitie with the Scriptures, and cannot afford them a good word, nor ſuch as love and owne them as the word of God, but ſeeke by all meanes to diſparage them, by calling them a dead letter, and carnall, and vaine, till men have them inſpired by the Spirit of God. As though it were wholy in vaine to reade them, or ſearch them, or heare them preached and opened, till they be inſpired by the Spirit of God into their minds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea:</hi> For in his 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> page he ownes that Scripture, 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 3.16. To wit, <hi>that all Scripture is given by inſpiration of God, and is profitable for doctrine, for reproofe, for correction, for inſtruction, that the man of God may be perfect,</hi> &amp;c. Saying that to whom they are given by inſpiration they are ſo, but what is this to the Devill, and falſe Prophets, who ſteale them, and have them not given by inſpiration, are they ſo to them?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Here hee diſcovers his old fathers policie and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine craftines; this wiſdome is herein manifeſt, <hi>not to be from above, but earthly, ſenſuall and devilliſh;</hi> for it proceedeth meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from <hi>envie and ſtrife;</hi> ſee <hi>James</hi> 3.14, 15, 16 &amp;c. <hi>And where envying and ſtrife is, there is ſedition and every evill worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe wee aske <hi>James Naylor,</hi> whether we may not lawfully reade the Scriptures which <hi>were written for our learning,</hi> till they be inſpired into us, and that we have them by inſpiration without reading them? What he would anſwer is a great queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but in all likelihood hee would make ſome evaſion, and not anſwer properly, either yea or no leaſt the Serpents head ſhould be too viſible, and ſo in danger to be broken by <hi>the ſword of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105464:7"/>Spirit, which is the word of God;</hi> yet wee may geſſe at his minde, to wit, that he accounteth it in vaine, at leaſt if not unlawfull to reade the Scriptures; For he telleth us plainly, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing gotten from Scripture but braine knowledge; and that the famine is greateſt of hearing <hi>the word of the Lord,</hi> where men trade moſt with Scripture, ſee page 7.</p>
            <p>And he would gather from that Scripture, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. that becauſe men <hi>that are unlearned and unſtable wreſt ſome things</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Scriptures <hi>to their owne deſtruction;</hi> Therefore it is a way for men to deſtroy themſelves, to uſe the letter of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or expect any helpe thereby as a way to God, whereof I forewarning them, ſaith he, and bidding firſt minde the light of Chriſt, and his Spirit to lead into the truth of thee. I am hated (ſaith he) and all the Devills inſtruments, who ſayes I may as well exhort them to looke to the Devill himſelfe for teaching, or leading, as to the light within.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Yea and this I ſaid, and ſay it here againe, that ſuch in whom the Devill ruleth for the preſent, as ſo he doth alwayes in the children of diſobedience, if they turne their minds inward, and follow ſuch light and motions as he ſuggeſteth, and doe but once get perſwaded that it is no other but the Spirit of God, their condition is ſad, but how much ſadder is his condition, that ſo perſwadeth them; as if the light of Chriſt, and that onely were in every man: oh wicked doctrine! what wiſdome is that before ſpecified then, <hi>that cometh not from above, but is earthly, ſenſuall, and devilliſh:</hi> and is therefore marked out by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle that it might be knowne, whence ſuch wiſdome cometh, and be avoyded.</p>
            <p>But though there is a <hi>wiſdome that cometh from above,</hi> I never read in all <hi>Naylors</hi> writings that he noted that out from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> doth but telleth us further that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill had much rather keepe people doing in the letter, that with the fallen wiſdome they might wreſt them then to be lead into the truth that the Scriptures declares of by the Spirit of truth, which leads into all truth, without which no truth is knowne, alledging <hi>John</hi> 16.13.</p>
            <p>I anſwer; Oh devilliſh doctrine! Nay rather a <hi>Doctrine of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills:</hi> This maketh me Recant that ever I charged ſuch doctrines
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105464:7"/>upon <hi>James Naylor,</hi> for he was but an inſtrument; this is moſt manifeſtly a doctrine of Devills; I meane the Devill writeth, and teacheth, and ſpeaketh ſuch doctrines by him as an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>For what minde hath the Devill or ever had that men ſhould reade, or heare, or obey the Scriptures; doth not the Devill know, that <hi>faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God,</hi> I meane by the eſſentiall word, who is pleaſed to <hi>open mens underſtandings, that they might underſtand the Scriptures,</hi> and that they might <hi>attend to the things that are ſpoken</hi> by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God, and by the Lord himſelfe in his holy Word, as <hi>hee opened the heart of Lidia, that ſhee attended to the things which Paul ſpake.</hi> And ſhall we thinke that it is of the Devill, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, when men frequent the preaching and hearing of the Word, and the reading and ſearching of the Scriptures? Is there any Scripture in all the Bible that ſo much as hinteth ſuch a doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine? And how ſhall men know what the Scripture declareth, if they doe not reade or heare them? And what is that to the matter, becauſe ſome heare and reade them, and doe not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, nor receive or beleeve and obey the ſame; muſt that be charged on the Scripture, as the cauſe, and muſt the Scripture be called carnall, and a dead letter, becauſe it doth not quicken, and give life to all that heare it. Is it not purpoſely ſent and made knowne to ſome, that it might <hi>convince them of ſinne,</hi> for their greater condemnation; and might be <hi>the ſavour of death unto death</hi> to ſuch as periſh. But it alwayes is <hi>the ſavour of life unto life unto them that beleeve.</hi> And as <hi>faith cometh by hearing</hi> of ſuch as <hi>are ſent,</hi> ſo faith, &amp;c the Spirit are miniſtred together, for he that hath faith, hath a meaſure of the Spirit, for the Spirit is miniſtred <hi>by the hearing of faith preached.</hi> One would have thought all the Devills in hell could not have deviſed ſuch a devilliſh doctrine to keepe men from hearing and reading the Scripture. If <hi>James Naylor</hi> would aske that lying ſpirit by which he is acted, how he may certainly know, <hi>the ſpirit of truth from the ſpirit of errour,</hi> the Spirit of God from the ſpirit of Satan, eſpecially when <hi>hee is tranſformed as an Angel of light,</hi> and comes with faire ſhews and pretences. I verily beleeve hee would never bring him ſuch texts of Scripture, as the Apoſtles have propoſ'd to be as certaine rules
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105464:8"/>and markes of tryall, but would rather tell him thoſe markes and rules are too carnall for them to obſerve that have already ſuch meaſures of the Spirit, and have been ſo proficient and active thereby, and ſo indeavour to put them out of all doubt, nor will hee ſuffer them to hould forth any ſuch markes unto others, but onely ingage them to obedience unto him, as he ſhall move and act them, and to beleeve and obey ſuch particular Scriptures as he bringeth to their minds, and applyeth and wreſteth for his owne ends. The Devill never bringeth Scriptures, but to deceive there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, alwayes wreſting them from their genuine ſenſe and proper meanings; as <hi>James Naylor</hi> might ſee if he were not blinde, or had not ſould himſelfe for the Devills ſervice.</p>
            <p>And againe whereas he ſaith that one may have the letter of Scripture, and not have the word, and that the letter without the Spirit is dead, <hi>page</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>I anſwer as before, that the letter of the Scripture is the word of God, though it is not Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And that the letter of the Scripture is no where in Scripture called a dead letter, but it is words of ſpirit and life, to <hi>them that beleeve and receive them in love,</hi> nor is the Spirit of God at any time withdrawne from his owne words, nor doe <hi>they returne voyde, but alwayes accompliſh what he pleaſeth, and doe that for which he ſent them:</hi> And it is not <hi>the Reſiſting of his Word or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> nor both joyntly, that can diſparage the validitie thereof, whether it be ſet home by the finger of his Spirit, or that mens hardned hearts ſtill remaine obdurate; Nor will <hi>James Naylors</hi> Directorie to a light within be effectuall to any for the ſaving of their ſoules that doe not beleeve the Scriptures <hi>and receive them in love, but have pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> but will rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger them to be deluded with a lying ſpirit, and acted by it in ſtead of the Spirit of God, and to be carried blind-fold to their greater ſinne and condemnation.</p>
            <p>And therefore what is that to the matter, though Satan have the Scripture, and have no good by it, there being no promiſe therein for him; or what if <hi>James Naylor</hi> hath it, and finde no life in it, but a meere dead letter, in his apprehenſion, in regard hee wreſteth it, and doth not love it, and therefore cannot af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford it ſo much as a good word, having an enmitie againſt it,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105464:8"/>not caring much if it were all burnt, as it is very likely, becauſe it condemneth him in ſomething or other that he loveth or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth, and will not part with, in obedience thereunto but will rather runne the hazzard of looſing all, or he will diſparage and make voyde the Scripture, that hath touched him; Nay, hee ſeemeth to mee rather to preferre his owne words and his owne writings above any in Scripture, commending his owne as words that proceed immediately from the eternall Spirit, full of life and power, but the Scriptures carnall and dead and vaine, yea vaine hee accounteth them to ſuch who have not the Spirit already: Though he cannot but know they are appointed of God as the cheife meanes for <hi>miniſtration of the Spirit,</hi> and of life and power, for what life and power can be communicated or adminiſtred to any man by miniſtration of men, but from Scripture-grounds, and thoſe pretious promiſes therein contained, through Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>in whom all the promiſes are yea and Amen,</hi> and through whom onely wee have intereſt in them; being all finners, and ſo excluded from life, as well as the Devill, were it not for him that hath merited our ſalvation. And therefore what a devilliſh doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is this to dehort all men from reading the Scriptures, till they firſt obtaine the Spirit of God; What other end can this doctrine aime at, but to keepe them ſtill under a ſpirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, as ſure there are none that are ſet free and have the ſpirit of life in them, through <hi>the hearing of faith preached,</hi> That will owne this doctrine to be of God, but <hi>a doctrine of Devills.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And againe, hee telleth mee that hee might ſhew my blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in all other Scriptures that I quote, were it needfull, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance that 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Wee have a more ſure word of propheſie, to which you doe well to take heed, as to a light that ſhines in a darke place, till the day dawne, and the day-ſtarre ariſe in your hearts.</hi> Now it is true I quoted this Scripture as one amongſt the reſt againſt his aſſertion in his anſwers to <hi>Baxter,</hi> to wit, (that the Scripture houlds out but one light and word) the which I there denyed, and proved it firſt from <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16. To wit, <hi>Yee are the light of the world;</hi> and <hi>John</hi> 5.35. that <hi>John was a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and a ſhining light;</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.130 <hi>The entrance of thy words giveth light, it giveth underſtanding unto the ſimple;</hi> and then this of <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:105464:9"/>
            <p> Upon which, I ſay, that I ſuppoſe <hi>James Naylor</hi> will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that he ever received any light from that ſure word of propheſie, <hi>as from a light ſhining in a darke place,</hi> but onely ſome little braine knowledge of the bare letter, elſe hee would not ſo reproach and diſparage thoſe, that <hi>doe take heed to the ſure word of propheſie,</hi> till they be inlightned thereby in what they were darke and did not underſtand. Now to all that I ſay in theſe words, hee anſwereth not at all by way of contradiction, but doth as much as confeſſe that hee was miſtaken, nor can hee poſſibly make that his aſſertion good againſt theſe Scriptures.</p>
            <p>But hee heere undertakes to ſhew my blindneſſe in quoting this Scripture to this purpoſe before-named to wit, And this (ſaith he) you would have to be the letter of the old Prophets, which <hi>ſhines in a darke place;</hi> And ſo ſaith hee, by thy doctrine the letter of the old Teſtament, and in a darke place too, is a ſurer word then what <hi>Peter</hi> heard God himſelfe ſpeake, and were <hi>eye witneſſes of his Majeſtie.</hi> And this is all thou knoweſt of the ſpirit of propheſie, the teſtimony of Jeſus, or the Scriptures that declare it.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that I appeale to the Judgements and Conſciences of all that know any thing of the ſpirit of propheſie, or the teſtimonie of Jeſus, or the Scriptures that declare it.</p>
            <p>Whether the Apoſtle doth not meane it of the old <hi>Propheſies</hi> of the old Teſtament, when he thus ſpeaketh; yea I ſay, the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee meant when hee ſo adviſeth them, and not the ſpirit onely, of which the letter declares; for the letter declares of the ſpirit, and the ſpirit is the author and opener of the letter; and that by the letter as an inſtrumentall meanes, comparing <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with Scripture, and ſpirituall things with ſpirituall things.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> himſelfe <hi>underſtood by booke that the time of their captivitie was accompliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>James</hi> the Apoſtle produced the words of the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> to Reſolve that great doubt and difference amongſt them, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.15. To wit, <hi>And to this agree the words of the Prophet, as it is written,</hi> &amp;c. Obſerve <hi>as it is written,</hi> and ſo he Recites the very written letter, for he knew by the letter what the words of the Prophet were becauſe they were written: And how elſe ſhould wee have knowne the words of the Prophets, if they had
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105464:9"/>not been written, and wee had ſeene or heard them read or reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, thoſe Prophets themſelves being dead long ſince: were they not <hi>written for our learning,</hi> and what good will their being writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten doe us, if we will not reade them, but ſtay and waite till they be inſpired into us, as ſo <hi>Naylor</hi> owneth the Scripture to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to whom they are given by inſpiration: Implying that elſe they are not, if we have them firſt by reading; ſee in this his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>page</hi> 5. What an abſurd doctrine is this, and how loath is he to owne that the Scripture in bookes is worth reading; This diſcovers what ſpirit hee is acted by, and how bitterly malicious and full of devices againſt the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>And againe obſerve the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> and hee are fallen at odds, and he hath given him the lye, for writing this Scripture; it hath ſo angered him that the Apoſtle ſhould ſtand in ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect oppoſition to his falſe doctrine.</p>
            <p>For the Apoſtle calls it <hi>a more ſure word of propheſie,</hi> then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther viſions, or voyces, which he had in the Mount: But this <hi>James Naylor</hi> denyeth and blameth mee exceedingly for belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch a thing, as that the letter of the old Prophets ſhould be a ſurer word, then what <hi>Peter</hi> heard God himſelfe ſpeake, and were eye witneſſes of his Majeſtie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ:</hi> I anſwer, this voyce and viſion might ſeeme a ſurer word unto <hi>Peter,</hi> and others, then the old propheſies it accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them; and ſo was a further confirmation of what the Prophets had ſpoken. But thoſe to whom he writes this Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch things, did not heare that voyce, nor ſee his Majeſtie, but had it written unto them as well as the Propheſies, and ſo had it but in the letter from <hi>Peter</hi> as a teſtimony unto them: And therefore it was that the Apoſtle called it <hi>a more ſure word of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie;</hi> for words of propheſie <hi>given by inſpiration of God,</hi> if wee know them to be ſuch, are more ſure words to me, then viſions and voyces that are heard by others, and ſeene and Related; For the teſtimony of Jeſus is the ſpirit of propheſie. And this hee would have them to know that <hi>the propheſie in old time came not by the will of man, but holy men of God ſpake as they were mooved by the Spirit of God.</hi> And therefore hee ſaith <hi>(wee)</hi> including himſelfe, <hi>have a more ſure word of propheſie,</hi> the which though the confirmation thereof to <hi>Peter,</hi> teſtifying of Jeſus to be the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105464:10"/>Chriſt, therein ſpecified, was ſurer to him, yet that ſure word of propheſie was a more ſure word to build their faith upon, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it foreſhewed the coming of Chriſt, and that that Jeſus was hee; giving notice beforehand of the place of his birth, and of his life and death, and all ſuch things which came to paſſe. Which clearely demonſtrateth that all thoſe propheſies were by inſpiration, for who elſe but God could foreſhew ſuch things ſo long before: And therefore there cannot be <hi>a more ſure word,</hi> then that <hi>ſure word of propheſie;</hi> for what can be ſurer then the words of God, and thoſe proved to be his words by the truth and ſucceſſe in the events thereof, that were thereby fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewed.</p>
            <p>And therefore it is that in caſe the people deſired to know of any Prophet, whether the Lord had ſent him with ſuch a Meſſage, or he had ſpoken it preſumptuouſly; Hee referres them to the ſucceſſe and events thereof, and whether the thing came to paſſe or no; ſee <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.21, 22. To wit, <hi>When a Prophet ſpeaketh in the name of the Lord, if the thing follow not, nor come to paſſe, that is the thing which the Lord hath not ſpoken, but the Prophet hath ſpoken it preſumptuouſly, thou ſhalt not be afraid of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the propheſies of old time are confirmed to us to be <hi>a ſure word of propheſie;</hi> and therefore we cannot but beleeve them. And that a great deale better then the propheſies of <hi>James Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor,</hi> though hee telleth us hee hath them by Immediate voyce, and viſions likewiſe, and that hee hath them from God by Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate inſpiration. For till we ſee them confirmed by the events thereof, wee ſhall rather beleeve that <hi>more ſure word of propheſie,</hi> that was ſpoken <hi>in old time,</hi> and alſo thoſe ſure words of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and Rules and directions given by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, then thoſe given by <hi>James Naylor,</hi> though hee call himſelfe, and others account him, the Meſſenger of the living God.</p>
            <p>But though wee doe beleeve in regard wee finde it in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and that in many places, and are in expectation dayly to ſee the downfall and ſhame and confuſion of ſuch who preſume to preach <hi>in the Name of the Lord, and hee hath not ſent them,</hi> ſee verſe 20. Yet wee dare not believe the propheſying of <hi>Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor</hi> in that reſpect, nor can we expect or deſire, either the down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105464:10"/>and ſhame and confuſion of any that is godly and faithfull; Nor dare wee condemne all that preach in publike (in our pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like places which hee whickedly calleth our Idoll Temples) to be carnall and hirelings, as he blaſphemouſly doth, for wee know the contrary, and therefore know him to be a lyar, and not a true Prophet; and ſo wee feare him not, nor regard his propheſies; but as falſe and frothie preſumptuous lyes; and therefore if it come not ſo to paſſe hee will be diſcovered to thoſe ſeely peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that for the preſent beleeve him, as ſo he is to us already.</p>
            <p>Againe, I produced a Scripture to prove the various and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent diſpenſations of the Lord to his Prophets, and to Rebuke the pride and inſolencie of <hi>James Naylor,</hi> the which, as I ſuppoſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could not oppoſe any deductions from it, nor evade the charge upon himſelfe, to wit, of deſpiſing the Word; He maketh as though he underſtood not my meaning, and as though I had brought it for another end the which I never meant; And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth uſe of it for prooving that they are no Prophets who have no word but the letter: The which I ſhall eaſily graunt; ſo hee will not deny that the letter of Scripture is the word; alſo nor did I ever deny it, but owned Chriſt as the eſſentiall word; and the Scripture alſo is the word; and therefore he needed not fetch any arguments to proove it. But I made another uſe of it, to wit, that I finde but little of this meekneſſe in <hi>James Naylor,</hi> that was exemplified in <hi>Moſes;</hi> But on the contrary, that hee counteth himſelfe the higheſt, and all below him either dwarfes or nothing like Chriſtians; in ſo much as if they have need of a booke, either the Bible, or any other, they are deſpiſed by him as litterall men in his booke againſt <hi>Moore.</hi> Though <hi>Paul</hi> adviſed otherwiſe, as <hi>to give attendance to reading, and to exhortation and doctrine,</hi> and not onely to a light within; and more to that purpoſe: Which is ſo quite contrary to his Directorie, that having nothing to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, he turneth the deaſe eare and falleth upon other buſines diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed before.</p>
            <p>Againe he ſaith my ſecond thing is to deny the light of Chriſt to be ſufficient.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, it is moſt falſe, I told him that wee muſt confeſſe that Chriſt is able to inlighten little children, and to make them capable of comprehending of it, and that ſo he doth to his Elect
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105464:11"/>that depart this life in their childhood and minoritie; for <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> was <hi>ſanctified in the wombe;</hi> and <hi>John Baptiſt filled with the Holy-Ghoſt from his mothers belly;</hi> and that Chriſt himſelfe was qualified with the bleſſed Deitie in the very <hi>ſeede of the woman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet conſidered as man hee did not in his minoritie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that light which <hi>dwelt in him bodily,</hi> but <hi>increaſed in wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſtature and favour with God and man,</hi> as <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.52. Yea though conſidered as God <hi>he thought it no robbery to be equall with God,</hi> yet as man hee was ignorant of <hi>the times and ſeaſons which the Father had kept in his owne power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay after he was aſcended and <hi>ſate downe at the right hand of the Majeſtie on high,</hi> when hee gave forth the <hi>Revelation</hi> of Saint <hi>John,</hi> hee had it but at the ſecond hand conſidered as man, for it is called <hi>the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt which God gave unto him to ſhew unto his ſervants things which muſt ſhortly come to paſſe, and hee ſent and ſignified it by his Angell unto his ſervant John:</hi> ſo that <hi>John</hi> had it but at the third hand, though he had Chriſt the light Recident in him; as ſo had alſo the ſeaven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and the Angells thereof, yet they had but this Revelation at the fourth and fift hand; therefore meanes are good.</p>
            <p>From all which it is evident, that though God can and doth when he ſeeth it good and neceſſary, communicate his light Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately by his bleſſed Spirit unto whom he pleaſeth.</p>
            <p>Yet his ordinarie way where meanes is to be had is <hi>by the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe of preaching</hi> (as ſo the world accounteth it) <hi>to ſave them that beleeve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore ſuch doctrines as theſe which tend ſo directly contrary to the uſe of meanes, are as abſurd and wicked, as if they ſhould teach their children not to eate any meate, becauſe God is able to preſerve them without. Nay it is ſo much worſe by how much the ſoule is better then the body.</p>
            <p>And this and many more ſuch like things I did aſſert in my Booke.</p>
            <p>But is there any thing heere againſt the ſufficiency of the light of Chriſt, or ſo much as intended, ſave onely I plead for the uſe of meanes, to get his light mediately or immediately, againſt which he hath nothing to anſwer, and therefore falls to cavill againſt a manifeſt truth, to wit, That after Chriſt was <hi>ſate downe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105464:11"/>on the Right hand of the Majeſtie on high,</hi> hee had the Revelation, conſidered as man, but at the ſecond hand; And makes great adoe as though hee did not underſtand what I meane by having it at the ſecond hand; and yet hee remembers I ſaid hee Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it of God, and yet is ſtumbled to know which was the firſt hand.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, God had it firſt, it was in his hand and power be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Jeſus Chriſt had it given to him; ſo that hee had it not firſt but at the ſecond hand; and this is plaine in the Text, for all his blind cavills: And then againe that <hi>John</hi> had it but at the third hand, I ſay it againe; And hee ſaith, is not this ſtrange doctrine of thine, and hee had it from <hi>the Alpha and Omega, the allmigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie;</hi> or did hee not ſpeake true who ſaid hee was ſo, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.8.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer; And did not hee ſpeake true that ſaid of Jeſus Chriſt, that <hi>hee ſent and ſignified it by his Angell unto his ſervant John;</hi> And is not Jeſus Chriſt in heaven; And muſt not <hi>the heavens containe him till all things be reſtored?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore it was not Jeſus Chriſt, conſidered as man, but his Repreſentative <hi>Michaell</hi> the Archangell, who Repreſentatively viſſibillified the Inviſible eſſence of the bleſſed Deitie of the Sonne of God, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in like manner, as alſo before his Incarnation, the Lord alwayes Repreſented himſelfe in the ſimilitude of a man when he ſpake unto the Prophets in viſion, as <hi>Ezekiell</hi> 1.25, 26. To wit <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the likeneſſe of the throne was the likeneſſe as the appearance of a man above upon it;</hi> And from thence <hi>came the voyce,</hi> ſee <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. <hi>From the firmament that was over their heads.</hi> But theſe were onely likeneſſes and ſimilitudes ſhewed in viſion by Angells, as the moſt proper ſimilitude of the preſence of the inviſible God; And therefore it is ſaid this was <hi>the ſimilitude of the glory of the Lord;</hi> clearely ſhewing that it was but a ſimilitude of his glory, and when the Prophet ſaw it he fell upon his face, and a voyce of one that ſpake, ſaying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſee <hi>verſ.</hi> 28.</p>
            <p>See alſo <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. What hee <hi>ſaw in his viſions by night,</hi> verſ. 9.13. Hee <hi>ſaw one live the Son of Man came with the clouds of heaven.</hi> But this was not the Son of Man, for hee was not then viſible in the world.</p>
            <p>And ſo I ſay of this <hi>Alpha and Omega,</hi> it was not the viſible
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105464:12"/>body of Chriſt, but onely a Repreſentation of the eſſentiall word, who is every where preſent in ſpirit at one and the ſame time, and doth ſometimes vocally expreſſe himſelfe to the capacities of his Prophets by the miniſtration of Angells: As ſo hee did alſo to <hi>John</hi> in this place, ſee <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.13. Hee is ſaid to be <hi>one like unto the ſonne of man, cloathed with a garment downe to the foote, and girt about the paps with a golden girdle, his head and haires were white, like wooll, as white as ſnow, and his eyes were as a flame of fire,</hi> verſ. 14.</p>
            <p>And without all queſtion Chriſt was preſent in ſpirit, and ſo expreſt himſelfe, as the <hi>Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end;</hi> and to be <hi>hee that liveth and was dead, and is alive for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, Amen.</hi> I ſay Chriſt was preſent even there in ſpirit, for ſo he is alwayes, and that every where <hi>to the end of the world;</hi> ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. But the ſpirit of Chriſt is <hi>inviſible, whom never man ſaw, neither can ſee;</hi> but through an eye of faith. Therefore this viſſibillitie that appeared unto <hi>John</hi> was not properly the eſſence of the Deitie which is <hi>inviſible,</hi> but God was there preſent, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſuch appearances and voyces by the miniſtration of Angells; For it is ſaid, <hi>Hee ſent and ſignified it by his Angell unto his ſervant John,</hi> verſ. 1.</p>
            <p>And ſo it is both true that the <hi>Alpha and Omega</hi> was there by viſion; and yet that it was but ſignified by voyce and viſion <hi>by an Angell,</hi> and ſo the <hi>Alpha and Omega</hi> did not lye, nor the Apoſtle neither.</p>
            <p>Neither was it any thing but truth which I aſſerted, to wit, that Chriſt conſidered as man, had it given him of God, and hee ſent and ſignified it by his Angell to his ſervant <hi>John,</hi> which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated it to the ſeaven Churches, but firſt to the Angells.</p>
            <p>And therefore the uſe I made of it is nothing but proper and true, nor can <hi>James Naylor</hi> deny the truth thereof with any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor the proprietie of the uſe I made of it, which is before related.</p>
            <p>But then againe hee telleth mee that I ſaid in my Epiſtle; One thing I dare ſay through the grace of God, here are divers argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and doctrines which have never yet that I know off been publiſhed before.</p>
            <p>To which hee anſwers: I ſay it ſeemes ſo, and that this is one
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105464:12"/>and the ſame I ſay too, that I never knew this publiſhed before.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that this one by his owne confeſſion, that hee never knew before, and hee cannot deny the truth thereof, nor the proprietie of the uſes of it that I make againſt him: And if it be a truth, hee hath learned ſomething that he knew not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore out of that little Treatiſe ſo undervalued by him, as fit for nothing but the fire; ſo that this peece of knowledge is come but mediately to him; for his light within did not teach it him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, nor would hee owne it now if hee could evade it; ſuch en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie hee hath againſt the truths of God, when they oppoſe his doctrines, and then hee murmurs extreamely, and meerely cavills with what I never deny'd; For I never deny'd the light of Chriſt to be ſufficient, if we have a ſufficiency of it; But onely plead for the uſe of ſuch meanes as God hath appointed to communicate it by; ſo that his grumbling and quarrelling is but as with his owne ſhadow.</p>
            <p>And whereas I queſtion him where the Scripture directs to give heed to a light within, and to deſert all teachings of men; in anſwer whereunto hee produceth <hi>Luke</hi> 11.35, 36. where hee telleth mee, I may ſee the counſaile of the onely Teacher. Now the words of the Scripture are, <hi>Take heede therefore that the light which is in thee be not darkneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If thy whole body therefore be full of light, having no part darke, the whole ſhall be full of light, as when the bright ſhining of a candle doth give thee light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe Scriptures are good and true, but I appeale to the Reader, whether there be any one word or ſyllable in them that requireth us to deſert the teachings of men, as a meanes to get tranſlated <hi>out of darkneſſe into his glorious light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And againe I queſtion him where the Scripture ſaith, that hee that <hi>is the light of the world, and lighteneth every one that cometh into the world,</hi> doth inlighten all ſufficiently, and ſo as to guide them infalliby, or that hee inlightneth all alike, and that Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately without the knowledge of the Scriptures, or the teachings of men, ſo as they need <hi>not to teach one another, ſaying, know the Lord, becauſe all doe know him from the greateſt of them, even to the leaſt of them.</hi> Is the caſe ſo now that all know him, what need is there then of the teachings of <hi>James Naylor,</hi> and his complices.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105464:13"/>If their light within them be ſufficient, it can teach them all that he doth, and all that he knoweth; and how to eye it onely, and to looke within for light, and to deſert and deſpiſe the teachings of men, as ſo he doth, and what elſe doth hee teach which is not taught by men from ſacred Scripture, and with more ſpirit and power then he teacheth any thing, and farre more rationally and convincingly, <hi>in the cleare evidence and demonſtration of the Spirit:</hi> And doth hee not herein teach men to deſpiſe his teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings alſo. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the firſt part of which queſtion hee anſwers, to wit, I ſay, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.12. to wit, <hi>I am the light of the world, hee that followeth mee ſhall not walke in darkneſſe, but ſhall have the light of life.</hi> And there (ſaith he) thou mayſt reade that hee that is the light of the world, his light is ſufficient to all that mind and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, I never denyed the ſufficiencie of his power and light to them that have ſufficient of it. But the queſtion is, whether he doth and will doe it to all or no, of all which this Scripture ſpeaketh not one word, nor that men ought to deſert the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of men.</p>
            <p>And therefore as I tould him, <hi>pag.</hi> 19. the queſtion doth not lye, whether the Spirit of God be an infallible guide, yea or no. But whether <hi>James Naylor</hi> and others be infallibly guided by that infallible Spirit yea or no, in all things that they doe: But to this hee turneth the deafe eare, and ſaith moſt falſly, that I plead againſt the ſufficiencie of the light of Chriſt; But I ſuppoſe he is aſhamed to meddle with an argument that hee cannot an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, leaſt diſcovering his weakneſſe, ſhould prove him fallible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and that hee hath very little of the light of Chriſt, but of that which comes from another ſpirit.</p>
            <p>And againe, hee blameth mee becauſe I ſay that Sathan is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to cloath us with good workes and doctrines, and that his Miniſters are tranſformed into Miniſters of righteouſneſſe, and thou ſayeſt thou cannot but rejoyce to ſee him play that card.</p>
            <p>To which hee anſwers, ceaſe thy babling, and ſee thy confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Is hee Sathan with thee, who cloathes with good workes and doctrines, and whoſe Miniſters are Miniſters of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Sathan is not ſo devided againſt himſelfe, nor his Miniſters
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105464:13"/>againſt their owne kingdome, though as to righteouſneſſe they pretend; but a righteous life, good words and good doctrines, hee that brings theſe forth was ever counted a Devill with thy generation.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that hee hath not tranſcribed my words aright, for I ſay that without queſtion Sathan is willing to cloake them with any (externall) righteouſneſſe, and with <hi>good words, and doctrines, and faire ſpeeches, to deceive the hearts of the ſimple,</hi> and eſpecially on condition that hee may but ſtabliſh their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, and draw men off from the uſe of meanes and ordinances, and from the teachings of men, and to neglect the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>For this would ſtill continue and increaſe his kingdome unto all generations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As it is further diſcuſſed and argued with Reaſons that hee can never evade: But being in a paſſion, like an angerie Curre, he muſt needs ſhew his teeth, though hee cannot bite. And let any rationall man judge, whether hee doth not ſhew his teeth againſt the Scripture it ſelfe; which ſaith plainly, <hi>And no marvaile, for Sathan himſelfe is tranſformed into an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of light, therefore it is no great thing if his Miniſters alſo be tranſformed as the Miniſters of righteouſneſſe, whoſe end ſhall be according to their workes;</hi> ſee 2 Cor. 11.14, 15.</p>
            <p>Doth he not plainely contradict theſe Texts, when he ſaith Sathan is not ſo devided againſt himſelfe, nor his Miniſters againſt their owne kingdome.</p>
            <p>How manifeſt is the hand of Sathan in this cleare contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the ſpirit of truth, by whom hee will not deny but the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpake; And yet hee dares be his inſtrument in writing for him.</p>
            <p>And againe hee ſaith, thou wouldſt compare us to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, who keepe people from the letter in their mother tongue; to which he anſwers, that the Devill did ſo as long as he could, who now would keepe in the letter.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, wee are like to take his word for it, in regard he hath no proofe but his owne teſtimonie; yet I beleeve hee telleth true in that which followeth, to wit that Sathan would keepe us from the Spirit what he can, in regard he would keepe us from the meanes whereby to obtaine it, and have it adminiſtred.</p>
            <p>And againe hee telleth mee, I ſay, where the Scriptures are
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105464:14"/>knowne and counted for the word of God, the Devills kingdome muſt downe in the heart.</p>
            <p>I ſay true, but I added in the hearts of the Elect; theſe words (of the Elect) he leaveth out, that hee might have ſomething to ſay. And hee leaveth out alſo the Reaſons there rendred, one whereof is our experience. What blindneſſe and darkneſſe and ſottiſh ignorance is in all places where the word is not preached, nor the Scriptures minded and ſearched and knowne, ſo that give him but the reception of this doctrine, and it is the beſt founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for his kingdome that can be laid; (and I ſay) it is like to that of the Papiſts, and hath the ſame tendency, to wit, that Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance is the mother of devotion.</p>
            <p>But the Scripture would teach them how to obtaine the ſpirit and wiſdome, namely, to <hi>aske it of God,</hi> which is none of <hi>Naylors</hi> directions in all his bookes, but quite the contrary, as to eye that light already within, as if every man had the Spirit already.</p>
            <p>And againe, ſaith he, thou calles it a groſſe directory, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe to take heede to a light within, and ſayes I might as well bid them follow the Devill.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, yes, I did ſay ſo, but he leaveth out my reaſon for it, to wit, in caſe where the Devill ruleth, and keepeth them in darkneſſe, as that hee doth <hi>in all the children of diſobedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But hee chargeth mee in anger, and telleth me hee ſayes I ſhall one day know I have blaſphemed againſt the ſpirit and gift of God herein: Was that, ſaith he, a groſſe directorie of Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.35. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.21.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, no, the firſt of theſe I have recited before, and the words of the other are theſe; <hi>Neither ſhall men ſay, loe heere or loe there, for the kingdome of God is within you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I ſay, here is never a word yet in any of theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that tendeth to perſwade men to looke onely to a light within, and deſert the Scriptures, and the teachings of men. But let any man judge whether the kingdome of God, and the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Sathan, can rule in the heart at one and the ſame time; is <hi>the kingdome of God come</hi> too and within ſuch a man whiles Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than ruleth? muſt <hi>hee not firſt binde or caſt out the ſtrong man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſpoyle his goods?</hi> Can any <hi>ſerve two Maſters?</hi> If the ſpirit of God and the ſpirit of Sathan can live quietly together in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105464:14"/>ſame ſoule, and not fight and quarrell and contradict each other in their motions and commands, Chriſt was deceived.</p>
            <p>It may be hee thinketh the caſe is ſo with every man, as it was with <hi>Toldervie,</hi> who was toſſed with croſſe commands of two ſeverall ſpirits, and knew not whether to obey, <hi>James Naylor</hi> might have taught him of all that time whiles hee continued his Diſciple, to have knowne the voyce of the Spirit of God from the voyce of Sathan if hee had knowne it himſelfe; for hee was long enough with them; But their skill is wanting to diſcerne of ſpirits; ſo that if it be a ſpirit within, they obey it as God, though hee hath forewarned them if they would heede the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; <hi>not to beleeve every ſpirit, but try them whether they be of God.</hi> And if they would learne of mee, I could give them Scripture Rules, to know for certaine what ſpirits they are of; but I am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt weary with ſtriving with them; and Scripture Rules are ſo ſlighted by them and ſo little regarded, that in reſpect of them I account it almoſt vaine, yet for the ſake of others, I ſhall name ſome few.</p>
            <p>And firſt to try the ſpirits whether they be of God in caſe of viſions or apparitions, yea dreames, or voyces, whether ſpeaking within or without.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Such who finde their hearts ambitious in ſeeking after viſions and Revelations, to get a fame and reſpect amongſt men, let ſuch ſuſpect all viſions or Revelations or apparitions what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, that appeare to them, as but deluſions of Sathan, ſent of God, either purpoſely to deceive them, or at leaſt to try them with, whether they doe more regard his holy and ſacred word, or the Revelations, viſions, or words of Angells.</p>
            <p>Yea <hi>though an Angell from heaven ſhould teach us another doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, then what wee have received</hi> from the word of God, wee are commanded, and therefore ought to <hi>let him be accurſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea though hee bringeth us many good meſſages, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth to many good things, yet if any part of his meſſage doth not really correſpond with the ſacred Scriptures, yea though he be an Angell of light, an Angell of God, an Angell from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and appeare in ſuch a ſhape as the holy Angells were accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to appeare in old time; yet beleeve him not, but rather let him be accurſed.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:105464:15"/>
            <p> Secondly, But obſerve alſo whether they appeare not to have cloven feete; For if ſo they may well be ſuſpected to be uncleane ſpirits, becauſe the holy Angells were never accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſo to appeare, but for the moſt part in the ſhape of a man when they brought any meſſage mediately from God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Obſerve whether they bring any meſſage of waight and Importance, and of neceſſitie, yea or no, ſuch as it much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes us to know, that we either cannot or have not learned or knowne before, or ſuch as cannot be knowne from Scripture, it being either ſilent therein, or that wee have not underſtanding to conceive it thence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea.</hi> For Idle and vaine meſſages are not likely to be from God, who forbiddeth all vanitie, yea ſo much as an Idle word.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, And much more, obſerve well their meſſage whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be lawfull to obey it yea or no, and try it by Scripture, and not onely by the doctrines of men, the <hi>Quakers,</hi> nor others, for all may erre; but the Scripture in its proper genuine ſence is infallible, <hi>true and cannot be broken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, Obſerve whether their meſſage hang properly and rationally together; For the Spirit of God and all his meſſages accord rationally together, and he likewiſe giveth underſtanding and rationalitie to ſuch to whom he ſendeth them to conceive them ſo.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Whether they inhibit any thing lawfull to be done, and that upon any penaltie, without a neceſſary cauſe or ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory reaſon for ſuch inhibition; For God is not unreaſonable in any thing hee requires, but convinceth the Judgement in any ſuch a caſe.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Obſerve whether their meſſage tendeth to puffe us up with pride and high conceits of our ſelves, as ſome choice men, when as yet wee finde no ſuch things in us above other men, eſpecially in reſpect of wiſdome and holineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea.</hi> For God doth not uſually commend any in ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe manner, nor ever any at all but ſuch who are really holy and wiſe and faithfull.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, Whether their meſſage tendeth not to bring us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſpirituall bondage; As to ſuch and ſuch wayes and formes, or ceremonies and practiſes, under paine of damnation, which doe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105464:15"/>not appeare to be abſolutely neceſſary, and that from Scripture grounds; But rather ſuſpect that they goe about to deſtroy our faith, by bringing us under a Covenant of workes, and ſo to keepe us in bondage, that wee can never attaine to <hi>a full aſſurance of faith,</hi> but as it were a doubtfull caſe depending wholy upon our good behaviour.</p>
            <p>For God requireth a <hi>full aſſurance of faith,</hi> and that in God, <hi>through Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> that ſo our <hi>Joy might be full,</hi> yea ſuch as is <hi>unſpeakable and full of glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For if our faith and aſſurance be not full, there is likewiſe a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in our love, and ſo by conſequence in our Joy in the Lord.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, And above all things obſerve whether their meſſage and buſineſſe tendeth to <hi>provoke us unto love and good workes,</hi> or unto <hi>wrath and bitterneſſe,</hi> or ſome diſpleaſure againſt our knowne brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rea.</hi> For he that biddeth us <hi>provoke one another unto good works,</hi> never doth provoke us to the contrary himſelfe, nor ought wee to obey <hi>if an Angell from heaven</hi> ſhould ſo provoke us, but <hi>let him be accurſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that wee might know how to diſcerne the motions and luſtings of the ſpirit and fleſh each from the other, that ſo wee might not be led blindfold to deſtruction by any deluding ſpirits within us nor without; take theſe Scripture Rules, to wit, ſee <hi>Gala.</hi> 5.16, 17. ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Walke in the ſpirit, and yee ſhall not fullfill the luſt of the fleſh: For the fleſh luſtech againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh; and theſe are contrary the one to the other; ſo that yee cannot doe the things that yee would.</hi> And on purpoſe that wee might be Reſolved how to know the one from the other, hee pointeth them out by their fruits, that ſo wee might know their tendency in the firſt motions or luſtings of them, and be lead by the ſpirit and not by the fleſh, to wit, ſee verſ. 19, 20, 21. ſaith he, <hi>Now the workes of the fleſh are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, which are theſe, Adulterie, fornication, uncleannes, laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Idolatrie, witchcraft, hatred, variance, emulations, wrath, ſtrife, ſedition, hereſies, envyings, murthers, drunkennes, revellings, and ſuch like: of the which I tell you before, as I have alſo told you in times paſt, that they which doe ſuch things ſhall not inherit the kingdome of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:105464:16"/>
            <p> Now it is eaſie to diſcerne if wee doe obſerve even the luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of our ſpirits in the firſt motion; whether they tend to the producing of any of theſe or ſuch like effects, yea or no, And ſo by the ſtrict obſervation of theſe Rules wee may Reſiſt them in their firſt motions, and <hi>mortifie ſuch evill and corrupt affections,</hi> in their firſt Riſe through the gratious aſſiſtance of the Spirit of God, whoſe fruits are alſo noted out for that purpoſe alſo that wee might know them and cheriſh and obey them, and be lead thereby, to wit, <hi>Love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering gentlenes, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, faith, meekneſſe, temperance, againſt which there is no Law;</hi> ſee <hi>verſ.</hi> 22, 23. To all which wee may joyne the <hi>wiſdome which cometh from above, which is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, and eaſie to be intreated, full of mercy and good fruits, without partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and without hypocriſie; and the fruit of righteouſneſſe is ſowne in peace of them that make peace;</hi> ſee <hi>James</hi> 3.17, 18. And further the Apoſtle ſaith in another place, that <hi>the fruit of the Spirit is in all goodneſſe, and Righteouſneſſe, and truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſee alſo 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4, 5, 6, 7. The nature or properties of love or charitie, to wit, <hi>Love ſuffereth long, and is kinde, it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyeth not, vaunteth not it ſelfe, is not puffed up,</hi> &amp;c As ſo I might be large in ſhewing the nature of that love which is a fruit of the Spirit, from every one of theſe properties. And likewiſe of the contraries; for the Scripture is full of ſuch directions and notes: As ſee on the contrary, for it is not the Spirit of God, but Sathan and our owne fleſh, that maketh men <hi>lovers of their owne ſelves, covetous, boaſters, proud, diſobedient to parents, unthankfull, unho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> &amp;c. ſee 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4, 5. But I muſt not inlarge ſo farre as to deſcant upon all theſe, and it is eaſie for any that will to try the ſpirits, and the tendencie of their motions, whether they lead us to good or evill, by which wee may eaſily know from whence they proceed. I ſhall therefore let theſe ſuffice for the preſent, and follow him a little further, to wit;</p>
            <p>He ſaith againe <hi>pag.</hi> 11 And thou ſayes, then what need the teaching of <hi>James Naylor,</hi> if this light within be ſufficient: I ſay, ſaith he as a meanes to turne people to this light I am, which the Devill uſeth all meanes hee can to turne them from.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that it is herein evident, that hee exalteth himſelfe above the light of Chriſt, and clearely diſowneth the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105464:16"/>ſufficiencie of that light for turning men to it, without the helpe of <hi>James Naylor,</hi> whom he ownes to be a meanes to turne them to that light. For as I ſaid before, ſo I ſay againe, that if all doe know the Lord already, what need is there then of the teachings of <hi>James Naylor,</hi> and his complices, if their light within them be ſufficient, it can teach them all that he doth, and all that hee knoweth, and how to eye it onely; and to looke within for light, and to deſert the teachings of men, and deſpiſe them too, as ſo hee doth</p>
            <p>And I ſay, doth not <hi>James Naylor</hi> teach that the light of Chriſt is ſufficient, and that without the teachings of men, or of the Scriptures; And yet confeſſeth himſelfe to be a teacher and a meanes to turne men to that light, ſhould hee not have added himſelfe to that light for making it up ſufficient, if it be not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient without him, as a meanes to turne people to it ſelfe, and direct them to eye it onely as the onely light, as ſo hee calleth it. And how is it the onely light, if it cannot inlighten people with ſo much light as to turne to it, and eye it onely, without <hi>James Naylor</hi> as a meanes.</p>
            <p>Now if <hi>James Naylor</hi> and his writings and teachings bee a meanes, and if hee alſo bringeth Scriptures to perſwade and turne men to eye that light; Why may not Scriptures be brought alſo by others beſides the <hi>Quakens,</hi> to <hi>turne men from darkneſſe unto light, and from the power of Sathan unto God.</hi> Where ſaith the Scripture, that <hi>James Naylor,</hi> and his complices, muſt needs be added as a meanes for turning men to God, and no body elſe, nor any other doctrine, but what <hi>James Naylor</hi> teacheth, muſt be uſed as a meanes, nor any Scriptures alledged but what hee bringeth, nor any expoſition, or meaning of the Scriptures given forth, but what hee giveth or approoveth: I appeale to all Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious men that reades theſe things, whether hee doth not clearely contradict himſelfe, and ſhew his owne conviction in this point by this his owne confeſſion and practiſe; and whether his owne conſcience can for ſhame deny it, that he is condemned out of his owne mouth, and his folly made manifeſt to all that reade or heare his words; a childe of ſeven yeares of age may diſcerne his folly and contradiction here, even to his owne doctrine. And then hee telleth mee that I ſay there are ſome that <hi>are a people of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105464:17"/>no underſtanding, therefore hee that made them will have no mercy on them.</hi> (And ſaith he) thou art hee who art reaſoning againſt the light of Chriſt being ſufficient, and yet thou ſayes is not <hi>the manifeſtation of the ſpirit given to every man to profit withall;</hi> haſt thou not loſt thy underſtanding herein?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, let all men Judge whether hee or I have loſt their underſtandings in theſe things; hee that hath manifeſtly contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted and convicted himſelfe in his own words, and blamed mee heere for producing ſuch grounds from Scripture, and arguments, as hee cannot anſwer with any reaſon at all, by way of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, but by aſſerting mee to be hee that is without underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not ſhewing in the leaſt any Reaſon at all why hee ſo calleth mee. But telleth mee that yet I have got the Serpents ſubtiltie, to thruſt in my words to abuſe the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, how can a men that hath loſt his underſtanding get the Serpents ſubtiltie, I never knew that any man could be ſubtile without underſtanding. And where I have thruſt in any of my words to abuſe the Scriptures; I cannot tell, nor <hi>James Naylor</hi> neither, and therefore this is one of his many lyes: But hee muſt ſay ſomething, elſe the <hi>Quakers</hi> will ſuſpect him that hee hath lead them wide, as if they will but reade his and mine, they may ſee who it is that hath got the Serpents ſubtiltie, to make evaſions where hee cannot anſwer, and make lyes and ſhifts that are very poore; What a poore ſhift is it to rayle and revile, in ſtead of Rationall anſwers.</p>
            <p>I ſaid in my booke alſo that ſome men are <hi>ſenſuall, having not the ſpirit;</hi> And is not the <hi>manifeſtation of the ſpirit given to every man to profit withall;</hi> and whom ſhall they profit, if all be alike qualified, and need no teaching? And is there not <hi>diverſities of gifts of that ſelfe ſame ſpirit,</hi> and all <hi>for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, till wee all grow up to a full ſtature,</hi> which is not yet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, no not by <hi>Naylor</hi> himſelfe, for all his boaſtings of infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie and pureneſſe from ſinne.</p>
            <p>To all which hee anſwereth not a word, but what is before Recited, which is nothing at all to the queſtions propoſed, but a poore Rationles evaſion, nor can <hi>James Naylor,</hi> nor that lying ſpirit by whom he is acted, with all his ſerpentine wiſdome and policie, evade the dint of theſe Texts of Scripture, but they quite
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105464:17"/>overturne all his maine doctrines againſt the uſe of meanes.</p>
            <p>For if theſe <hi>diverſities of gifts and manifeſtations of the ſpirit</hi> are given of God for <hi>the edification of the body of Chriſt, and for the worke of the miniſterie, and to profit withall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then they ought to be employd for that very end; and <hi>not to be put under a buſhell,</hi> nor hid as the <hi>talent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the wiſdome of God hath thought it fit to <hi>give gifts unto men for edifying of the body, and for the worke of the miniſtrie,</hi> and alwayes hath done and doth ſtill by inſtrumentall meanes communicate light and knowledge of ſpirituall things to all his people, and that by times and meaſures as it pleaſeth him, and by whom hee pleaſeth.</p>
            <p>Is it not a high preſumption in <hi>James Naylor,</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, to deny ſuch meanes and Inſtruments to be of any uſe in the Church, and goe about to perſwade all men to neglect and deſpiſe and diſparage ſuch meanes and inſtruments what in them lyeth, and onely direct them to turne their minds inward to what light they have within, and that already.</p>
            <p>Doe they not herein manifeſtly contradict the wayes and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, as accounting themſelves wiſer then hee, and as if his gifts were given in vaine, and not to be uſ'd or employd for any ſuch ends; as <hi>to the uſe of edifying,</hi> and as accounting it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that <hi>all things ſhould be done to the uſe of edifying,</hi> and that <hi>of the body,</hi> yea that men ſhould <hi>edifie one another in their most holy faith,</hi> yea after they have faith they may be <hi>built up further,</hi> and <hi>increaſe their faith,</hi> and <hi>walke from faith to faith,</hi> till they be tall and ſtrong, and <hi>full of power by the ſpirit of the Lord,</hi> if they uſe ſuch meanes as the Lord hath appointed them.</p>
            <p>But if all have light, and that ſufficient light already within, what need is there then of <hi>edifying one another, of the worke of the miniſtrie,</hi> yea of thoſe <hi>diverſities of gifts, and adminiſtrations and operations</hi> given forth <hi>by the ſame ſpirit;</hi> doth not <hi>hee that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſieth, ſpeake unto men to edification, and exhortation, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</hi> And ought wee not to <hi>covet earneſtly the beſt gifts:</hi> And <hi>are all Prophets, or all Teachers,</hi> to whom then ſhall they propheſie, or whom ſhall they teach? <hi>If all were one member, where were the body? If all were an eye, where were the hearing?</hi> ſo if all were tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, where were the hearers, who muſt learne? <hi>If the eare ſhould
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105464:18"/>ſay, becauſe I am not the eye, I am not of the body; is it therefore not of the body?</hi> So ſay I, if the hearers ſhould ſay, becauſe wee are not teachers therefore wee have not the ſpirit; have they therefore not the ſpirit? If <hi>James Naylor</hi> ſay ſo, I will not beleeve him; Becauſe I know that the wiſdome of God hath ſo <hi>tempered the body together,</hi> as that <hi>the eye cannot ſay to the hand, I have no need of thee; neither the head to the foot, I have no need of you;</hi> And this hee hath done purpoſely, <hi>That they might be no ſchiſme in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall body,</hi> that <hi>are all baptized into one ſpirit;</hi> ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. Cha. But if there be need one of another, then wee need helpe one of another, both the hearers of their teachers, and the teachers of their hearers: Teachers are as the eyes for guidance and lighting of the body, and hearers are as the eares which receive their tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings, and light, and directions for underſtanding and practicall obedience, as from the mouth of the Lord.</p>
            <p>And therefore till I ſhall be perſwaded that the wiſdome of <hi>James Naylor</hi> is above the wiſdome of the Lord himſelfe, I ſhall never beleeve that it cometh of wiſdome to direct men onely to a light within as their onely guide, and to neglect the miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and teachings of men, and of the Scriptures, as <hi>James Naylor</hi> doth: And that without the leaſt warrant or ground from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or reaſon either, as hath been ſhewed before. Nor hath hee yet done, nor can hee ever ſhew any the leaſt Scripture that ſo much as tendeth to ſuch a doctrine, nor his ſpirit neither: But theſe evading, ſhifting, reviling anſwers, in ſtead of rationall and proper anſwers, doe clearely hould forth his conviction and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance againſt the light it ſelfe, concerning this maine point ſo much controverted: I ſhall therefore follow him to ſome other point; to wit, hee telleth mee <hi>pag.</hi> 15. that I aske in what part of Scripture is the Goſpell called the letter, or the preaching of faith, the preaching of the letter; I ſay, thou ſhouldſt aske thy ſelfe this queſtion, who would make the letter the Goſpell, and the preaching of faith litterall; which I ſay are both ſpirituall, and ſpiritually preached. And I aske thee againe, where did ever I call the Goſpell letter, or the preaching of faith letter, and ſo take thy challenge backe againe.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that I tould him that I finde it in a little booke written by <hi>Thomas Polard</hi> in anſwer to <hi>Richard Farn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:105464:18"/>that they call the Scriptures carnall, and a dead letter, and ſay it will never bring a man to the knowledge of God, but that all that is gotten from the Scripture, is but braine knowledge.</p>
            <p>And that I finde in a booke of <hi>Naylors</hi> againſt <hi>Thomas Moore,</hi> how hee anſwereth this, to wit, being asked by <hi>Moore</hi> whether the writing of the Prophets and Apoſtles be a dead letter; hee anſwereth, that without the Spirit it is; ſee in my booke <hi>pag.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. And it is cleare in the 12 <hi>page</hi> of this his anſwer, where hee ſaith, ſpeaking of the Devill that hee would keepe in the letter, but from the ſpirit, of which the letter declares. And ſaith alſo to us and the reſt of the world, you have long counted the Scriptures to be the word of God; but the Devills kingdome is ſtanding ſtill in the heart, and ſo muſt be till there be account of the word, that is nearer then the letter.</p>
            <p>From all which expreſſions it is cleare, that that which wee call the Scriptures, hee calleth the letter, and a dead letter.</p>
            <p>Now wee call the contents of the Bible, both the old and new Teſtament, the holy Scriptures, and ſo hee will not deny but they are. Now theſe Scriptures hee owneth but as carnall and a dead letter; wee call them ſpirituall, and the words of God.</p>
            <p>Therefore hee calleth all the Scriptures, the letter. And the Goſpell being contained in the Scriptures, which is <hi>glad tydings and good newes, that ſhall be to all people;</hi> the which was therefore called the Goſpell. And it was <hi>written for our learning, that wee through patience and comfort of the Scriptures might have hope;</hi> the which Goſpell was alſo preached from the beginning, yea even to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> that they might have hope and comfort thereby, to wit, that <hi>the ſeede of the woman ſhould breake the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head.</hi> And wee ſhall not deny that the Goſpell is ſpirituall, and ſo is the Law alſo. But wee muſt not deny, but both this Law and Goſpell <hi>are written for our learning.</hi> And if they be written, it muſt needs be legible to us, or it will not ſerve for our learning, if wee want it for the preſent, and have it not written in our hearts; for if <hi>faith come by hearing,</hi> and ſo by reading, as ſo it doth ſometimes, then it entereth firſt by the eare, to wit, by hearing, or elſe by the eye, to wit, by reading. And if wee cannot reade what is written in the hearts of one another (not being omnitient) but by hearing them ſpeake, or ſeeing them act,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105464:19"/>or reading an expreſſe of their minds in writing: how can wee learne what is the minde and will of the Lord, from that which is written, if it be not legible, and that in letters: Suppoſe us as ignorant for the preſent, not having either Law or Goſpell as yet in our hearts; how ſhall wee beleeve in him, in whom wee have not heard? Implying that it is not a thing to be expected, that all ſhould have it by Immediate inſpiration, but by the hearing of it preached, which is the ordinarie meanes whereby the Lord conveyeth it to the ſoule, as hath been ſhewed before, and that from Scripture grounds. Now that which hee calls the letter, wee call the Scripture, and ſo it is, for it was written, and is therefore Scripture, becauſe written; yet wee dare not call it a dead letter, but <hi>lively Oracles,</hi> a ſpirituall word, a word in which there is <hi>ſpirit and life</hi> to <hi>ſuch as beleeve and receive them in love;</hi> yea wee doe call the Scripture the word of God; And doe but aske <hi>James Naylor</hi> what elſe that is which is called by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>the ſword of the Spirit, which is the word of God:</hi> If it be not the Scripture, yea that which is written in the Bible, which hee calleth the letter; ſee <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.17. Aske him I ſay, whether this <hi>ſword of the ſpirit,</hi> which the Apoſtle calleth the word of God, be meant of Chriſt, who is the eſſentiall word, and who is the ſpirit, or it be meant of the Scriptures, which are the expreſſe word of God, and ſo as a ſword or weapon in the hand of the ſpirit, both defenſive and offenſive againſt our adverſaries upon all occations; yea Chriſt himſelfe uſed it againſt the Devill, when hee tempted him, and againſt the Scribes and Phariſees, and that as the beſt and fitteſt weapon to incounter them with.</p>
            <p>But if this ſword of the ſpirit be not the ſpirit it ſelfe, but the ſword or inſtrument in the hand of the ſpirit, and yet is called <hi>the word of God:</hi> Then it is not blaſphemy but good Scripture language to call the Scripture, <hi>the word of God;</hi> but the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my is theires, who call it carnall, and a dead letter, as hath more largely been ſhewed before in this Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>Now in theſe expreſſions of <hi>James Naylor,</hi> hee denyeth to call any thing Goſpell but the ſpirit, or any thing Scripture but the ſpirit, or any thing the word of God, but the ſpirit; And ſo the Scripture with him, and the glad tidings of the Goſpell con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein, muſt of neceſſitie either be called the ſpirit, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105464:19"/>ſo alſo God; or but a dead letter, and not <hi>the word of God,</hi> and ſo not the <hi>ſword of the ſpirit;</hi> wherein how clearely contradicteth himſelfe, and his owne confeſſions, as hath been ſhewed before, and alſo the plaine expreſſe Scripture, as any Rationall man may eaſily perceive, that will but reade and conſider, ſo that his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction is cleare from his owne confeſſions, concerning theſe two maine points of his doctrine, which I may well call the maine ſubſtance of that Goſpell which hee preacheth, and of all his bookes which hee writeth, namely, to teach us to eye that ſpirit, and word, and light within, and deſert the Scriptures, and the teachings of men, as a dead and vaine and fruitleſſe meanes for leading into and guiding in all the wayes of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The which Goſpell I now leave to the Judgements of all that are truely Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious whether it be not another Goſpell then the Goſpell of Chriſt, yea or no ſee <hi>Gala</hi> 1.8. And if hee doth not repent, his Judgement is paſſed already by the ſpirit of truth who cannot lye.</p>
            <p>And then againe hee beginneth to charge mee for pleading for Reverent geſtures to worſhip God in, as well as in ſpirit: The which I confeſſe I did; For <hi>page</hi> 27. I asked where it is ſaid in Scripture that God is not to be worſhipped with reverend ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of the body, as well as <hi>in ſpirit and truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which hee anſwereth; And whereas thou art pleading for reverend geſtures to worſhip God in as well <hi>as in ſpirit,</hi> I ſay, in at that doore came your Altars, your bowings, your ſurplices and conformities, wherein the teachers of this Nation was leading back to <hi>Rome,</hi> the mother of theſe witchcrafts, if God had not ſtopt the way by his hand: And now have you got a little peace, and thither are you turning againe, even in bloody perſecuting againſt all who witneſſe againſt you, who teſtifies againſt theſe falſe wayes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that for ought I know there is no man en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to worſhip either with Reverend geſtures or without, nor any man perſecuted or troubled for any ſuch things by any of the powers of this Nation. And therefore this is a lye and a ſlander againſt thoſe in Authoritie, as is well knowne, I need not proove it.</p>
            <p>But I onely asked whether the Scripture forbid Reverend ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105464:20"/>of the body, as well as in ſpirit and truth.</p>
            <p>To which he doth not anſwer properly, but ſheweth his diſlike thereof, and that they teſtifie againſt ſuch falſe wayes and geſtures ſet up by the man of ſinne. In which he clearely condemneth the practice of Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.41. And of <hi>Poter,</hi> Act. 9.40. And of <hi>Paul.</hi> Chap. 20.36. <hi>&amp;</hi> Chap. 21.5. &amp; <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.14. And of <hi>Daniell,</hi> Dan. 6.11. And of <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 Kings 8.54. and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.13. And that as unlawfull, and the pleading for the lawfullneſſe of it an opening of a doore to Altars and bowings, Surplices and conformities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and a making way for an unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralelld perſecution, and a haſting on to deſtruction, which he ſees, ſaith he, to be the end of our Reverend geſtures. And ſaith he, will not the geſtures of the Saints ſerve your worſhip, that which lookes ſo much out, neglects that within, ſo you plead againſt the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Oh prophane and ungodly ſpirits! It is not enough with them to ſlander the Magiſtrates, and all that are in authoritie, but they will ſlander the <hi>footſteps of the Lords anoynted,</hi> even the Lord Jeſus himſelfe, and all his anoynted ones, from the beginning of the world, who have all practiſed ſuch Reverend geſtures in their worſhipping of God: And then he ſaith, will not the geſtures of the Saints ſerve your worſhip? Oh damnable hypocriſie! are they Saints that reproach the practiſe and <hi>footſteps of the Lords anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;</hi> ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.51. ſee whoſe enemies they are. And doe they not therein Reproach the footſteps and wayes and geſtures of all the Saints that ever lived on the earth: And yet they will call themſelves Saints, as ſo alwayes did the Popes and Papiſts, that were Devills incarnate, and as abſolute enemies to the Saints of God, and ſo by conſequence to the Lord himſelfe, as any in the world: But for all his ſcornes it is the practiſe of the Saints that will ſerve our worſhips, and all the Saints geſtures that were Saints indeed, wee cordially approve and account it lawfull to follow their ſtepps, as occaſion requires; But as for the geſtures of Saint <hi>James Naylor,</hi> nor theſe his doctrines and ſlanders, they will not ſerve our worſhips to approve or practiſe, becauſe the Spirit of truth and holines Ingageth us otherwiſe, wee are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ingaged by the Spirit of God out of Reverend Reſpect to his glorious Majeſtie, to <hi>ſerve him with Reverence and godly feare;</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:105464:20"/>knowing that hee that is <hi>our God is a conſuming fire;</hi> ſee <hi>Heb</hi> 12.28, 29.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>hee that privily ſlandereth his neighbour, ſhall be cut off;</hi> ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.5. <hi>Of how much ſorer puniſhment ſhall hee be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthy</hi> that ſlandereth and Reproacheth even <hi>the ſonne of God</hi> and his Reverend geſtures in his prayers unto God. Can this be any leſſe then cleare <hi>deſpite unto the ſpirit of grace,</hi> ſee <hi>Heb</hi> 10.29. <hi>It is a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the living God;</hi> ſee verſe 31.</p>
            <p>It is no ſtrange thing to mee to reade his ſcornes, and reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and ſlanders, and cenſures, that in all his bookes hee hould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth, and fumeth out moſt bitterly and maliciouſly againſt others, or my ſelfe, conſidering his fullneſſe of venome and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice cannot be kept in, but muſt burſt forth like filthy vomit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>the Lord of glory,</hi> as in this appeares: I ſhall not therefore much care, nor take any great notice what hee ſaith by mee, but ſhall as breifly as poſſible anſwer his maine points, and referre the Reader to the bookes themſelves for Reſolution where the wickedneſſe lyeth; for I deſire no more but that they reade them both, and then let them Judge.</p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>Pag.</hi> 15. hee falleth to worke about the Miniſters, which is the third maine head, ſaying, Thy third thing is for thy maintenance, and for thy Miniſterie.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, as for my maintenance, there is not one word in all my booke, as the Reader may ſee, and that hee maketh lyes his Refuge, when hee hath nothing to anſwer that is like the truth.</p>
            <p>And as for Miniſters maintenance, and for the poore, I have pleaded it, and prooved it alſo, and that from divers grounds and arguments from Scripture, yea and Goſpell foundations, ſuch as <hi>James Naylor</hi> never heard before, nor have they been publiſhed before, that I know off, either by word or writing, as I ſaid in my Epiſtle, the which hee calleth boaſting, but doth not, nor cannot make it appeare to the contrary in the leaſt; neither can hee contradict the truth thereof, nor blame them juſtly, by any Rationall or ſpirituall argument, though hee reciteth many of them, as though hee intended a confutation, but in the end cometh off with a faile; perverting both my words and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105464:21"/>that hee might finde breadth for a Reproofe, which are but poore ſhifts, for ſo eminent a <hi>Quaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For ſaith hee, and that thou may get ſomething, or make a ſhew for this Religious worke thou art about, and that thou may ſeeme to be a charitable man, as <hi>Judas</hi> did, thou putſt in the <hi>poore</hi> with them, but ſeeing there is as much difference betwixt them and the poore, as betwixt Maſters and beggers, I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſet the poore by themſelves, concerning whom, I ſay, be as liberall to them as thou wilt.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that for my ends in this hee muſt not be Judge. But for what cauſe hee ſhould ſet apart the poore by themſelves, who were ever joyned together by the Lord himſelfe; when tithes were commanded, they to have part, as ſee. And whom God hath joyned together, I dare not ſeperate: neither did the Apoſtles in the primitive times, but what was given was <hi>diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to all as every one had need.</hi> But <hi>James Naylor</hi> dare, though hee hath his ground to ſeeke, for hee ſheweth no reaſon worth mentioning. I ſuppoſe hee was affraid with <hi>Judas,</hi> leaſt hee ſhould not ſeeme charitable to the poore, for under pretence of the poore, ſo hee could keepe it from the Miniſters of Chriſt, and ſo from Chriſt himſelfe; hee would have it for himſelfe, and the <hi>Quaker</hi>-Miniſters, to fill their baggs, though they are theeves and Robbers ſpiritually, as <hi>Judas</hi> was carnally; For it is evident that hee accounteth no poore deſerving, nor no Miniſters deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, but the <hi>Quakers</hi> poore and Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Though hee ſaith, if they be found Miniſters of Chriſt, farre be it from mee to hould from them that maintenance which Chriſt ever allowed his Miniſters. But that hee alloweth none to be found his Miniſters, but the <hi>Quaker</hi>-Miniſters is evident; for as for all ſuch as preach in our publike places, which hee calle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our Idoll Temples; are condemned by him as Miniſters of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and not ſent of God. So that hee and I are at a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from accordance, though hee ſeemeth to graunt to all that I plead for, or ever intended it, to wit, ſuch as are found to be Miniſters of Chriſt. Nor have I in the leaſt pleaded for any other, if they be knowne to be ſuch. And therefore though hee Imperiouſly commandeth mee when I write againe firſt to prove them ſo, and then call them ſo.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:105464:21"/>
            <p> I anſwer, I called not any by name, nor doe I know but few of very many that are knowne faithfull labourers in Gods har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, therefore I cannot enter into any particulars, it would be too large to proove every particular Miniſter of Chriſt ſent of God, by the particular grounds and Reaſons to cleare every man that yet is cleare in the ſight of God. But I am not ſo omniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; yet if I heare them preach in the cleare evidence and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the ſpirit and of power, by that I can know them, though I cannot demonſtrate the ſame unto <hi>James Naylor,</hi> as ſuch I know many, that preach in our publike places, which yet are but a few in compariſon of what there is that I know not, nor ever ſaw; Nor will I goe about to decipher them out by their markes, ſo as to condemne all as hee hath done, yet if they be <hi>Wolves</hi> that <hi>come in ſheepes cloathing,</hi> or meere <hi>hirelings,</hi> or clearely Antichriſtian, or if by any of their fruits I can certainly <hi>know them</hi> to be <hi>theeves and Robbers,</hi> and ſuch as are carnall and worldly, and proud and vaine boaſters, or heretickes, or ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, and ſuch like, I ſhall and doe diſowne them as much and more then <hi>James Naylor</hi> doth.</p>
            <p>But amongſt the Reſt I diſowne <hi>James Naylor</hi> in particular, for being ſo much as like any Miniſter of Chriſt that ever was in the world. But dare maintaine him for one of the primeſt of all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>athan hath, and the moſt audacious in a bad cauſe.</p>
            <p>Now hee telleth mee further, that another argument I uſe, ſaying, wee ought to account them as ſpirituall Fathers, And ſaith, that if any ſo doe whom they have not ſpiritually begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſuch account of a lye, and thou teaches them to it.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, That is one of <hi>James Naylors</hi> lyes; for if they be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to others, and I know it, though they did not beget mee, yet I ought to account them ſo, elſe I account of a lye above the truth: oh ſhameleſſe lyar! who but will know this to be a lye at the firſt reading; If they be fathers they are ſo, though not to mee.</p>
            <p>But for all thoſe markes that <hi>James Naylor</hi> hath given to know them by, I will not follow him throughout, Becauſe that this I know, That if they be ſuch who have the <hi>manifeſtation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and preach <hi>in the evidence and demonſtration thereof, and that with power,</hi> Though I ſee in them many humane frailties; and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105464:22"/>that they be <hi>ſubject to like paſſions as other men are,</hi> nay though <hi>Jonas</hi>-like they ſhould ſhew themſelves angerie with the Lord himſelfe, and that for ſhewing mercy, and ſay, they <hi>doe well to be angerie, even to the very death;</hi> yet I ſhall not deny but they are ſent of God, and ought to be maintained as his faithfull Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, and hee that denyeth them denyeth Chriſt, and hee that condemneth and Judgeth them as no Miniſters of Chriſt, becauſe of ſuch paſſions and frailties; doth alſo condemne and Judge himſelfe for the ſame cenſure that hee caſteth upon them, if hee doth the ſame or worſer things; It Redoundeth to himſelfe by the Judgement of the Lord; for ſaith hee, <hi>With what Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment yee Judge, yee ſhall be Judged.</hi> And therefore <hi>James Naylor</hi> hath cauſe to feare that Judgement attendeth him, and will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall him, and that ere long, if hee doth not repent; eſpecially af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Conviction in his owne Conſcience, of his injurious Cenſures and blaſphemous Reproaches, caſt like a flood out of his mouth and penn, to make them all odious amongſt the people of God: But I muſt not ſtand any longer upon this third particular, but ſhall fall to anſwer breifly, his Catalogue of lyes that hee would father upon mee, but may keepe them himſelfe, as more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his owne: For</p>
            <p n="1">1. Saith hee Thou ſayes our ſpirit teacheth us to pull downe mens faith and hope they have in God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> True, and that by calling men carnall and damned, when you cannot proove any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That wee give no honour or worſhip, either to God or man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not that I know off, let them ſhew wherein.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That we have no knowledge of God at all, but a wicked lying malicious ſpirit, that is an enemy to all goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> And ſo I verily beleeve, and that for thoſe reaſons ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in the booke.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That our wicked lying ſpirit teacheth us to ſpeake evill of all men, that embrace not our lying doctrines and wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The truth of this I Referre to the Judgements of all that know their Rayling and Reviling of the Miniſters and profeſſors of all ſorts, the <hi>Quakers</hi> excepted, who onely embrace their wayes.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:105464:22"/> 5. That the Elect may be ſo farre <hi>lead away with the errour of the wicked, as to fall from their owne ſteadfaſtneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſay, from their owne (proper) ſteadfaſtneſſe they may, which word (proper) hee leaveth out, to deceive the ſimple; And ſo I ſay, they may, elſe the Apoſtles exhortation was needleſſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the caſe is Juſt with us deluded <hi>Quakers,</hi> as it is with Witches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> And ſo it is in thoſe Reſpects therein mentioned, as I could have prooved it by examples of ſome of thoſe people.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That wee bitterly Revile and Reproach all the Saints and ſervants of God, almoſt over all the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> And I ſaid true; for they Revile and Reproach all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors but of their owne way, and thoſe are no Saints, but more like Devills.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That our pleading for ſo many good things, and ſharply reprooving of evill, and our coming to the light with the deeds, can be no other but from a deluding ſpirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſay it is true; for that is but done to delude the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple through hypocriſie, to make their lyes more feizible, as ſo the Miniſters of Sathan are ſometimes tranſformed as if they were Miniſters of Righteouſneſſe, as hath been ſhewed before, and ſo are they.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That our directing to obſerve the light in the Conſcience, is nothing elſe but to adviſe them to obey Sathan.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſay true in ſuch caſes wherein I inſtanced, to wit, to them in whom hee Ruleth; it is no better but ſo.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That wee direct people to eye and obſerve that lying ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that is in them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> So they doe by ſuch directions to all thoſe whom they ſo direct, in whom hee raigneth.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That <hi>Naylors</hi> doctrine is quite contrarie, that any that lacke wiſdome ſhould aske it of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſay in my booke Juſt ſo, and ſhew my Reaſons for it, becauſe I finde it not in any of his bookes: But onely a direction to ſeeke it within before they have it: And if they have it not already, then they want it, and ought to aske it of God, and not to ſeeke it where it is wanting, and not to be found; but it is a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105464:23"/>groſſe directorie ſo to adviſe them as ſo I call it in my booke.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That Sathan hath got a Commiſſion to be a lying ſpirit in my mouth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Very true, and if hee call this a lye, hee muſt father all theſe lyes himſelfe, and ſo be a Devill, and the father of lyes; for it is not God, hee cannot lye.</p>
            <p n="13">13. That <hi>James Naylor</hi> is ſent with ſtrong deluſions to ſome that they might beleeve a lye</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> True, and that to very many of thoſe that beleeved not the truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe; as ſo I ſay it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and ſhewed reaſons for it in my booke.</p>
            <p n="14">14. That I would needs be accounted ſome great Prophet, and to have ſome extraordinary revelations that no man elſe had knowne before, and yet teacheth us nothing except lyes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſay it is true, hee that teacheth us nothing (except lyes) but what wee knew before, now this (except lyes) hee leaveth out, and putteth in &amp;c. as was uſuall in the Biſhops times when they were aſhamed to declare all.</p>
            <p n="15">15. That <hi>James Nayor</hi> utterly denyeth the manhood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> So hee doth by cleare conſequence from his doctrine, as is prooved in the Treatiſe, for that hee blameth us for own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Chriſt without, and at a diſtance, to wit, his body being in heaven as well as hee is preſent with us in ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="16">16. That I blame men for praiſing and ſinging of Pſalmes in ſpirit unto God, as the Apoſtles did.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In ſpirit and with the mouth and voyce hee doth, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them Devills Rymes, moſt wickedly and prophanely, as is ſhewed, but not anſwered yet.</p>
            <p n="17">17. That I often produce the non-proficiency of the people as a ground of diſparagement to the word it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> So hee doth as a diſparagement to the Scripture it ſelfe, which I call the expreſſe word of God, and as a diſparagement to the teachings of men alſo; which hee cannot deny, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is his lye.</p>
            <p n="18">18. That <hi>James Naylor</hi> counteth himſelfe the higheſt, and all below him either dwarffes, or nothing like Chriſtians.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:105464:23"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> And this is true, for Reaſons therein ſhewed, but is his Recitall hee leaveth out thoſe words, to wit (either like dwarffes) and alſo the reaſons which hee cannot anſwer.</p>
            <p n="19">19. That I Reproach and diſparage thoſe that take heede to the ſure word of propheſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> True; for ſo hee doth all that take heede to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which the Apoſtle meant when hee ſo called it.</p>
            <p n="20">20. That how the word was made fleſh, <hi>James Naylor</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> True; I ſaid ſo, let him proove the contrary, by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it if hee can.</p>
            <p n="21">21. That <hi>James Naylors</hi> Directorie is quite contradictorie to the directorie of Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> True; and it is ſo prooved in the booke.</p>
            <p n="22">22 That I <hi>Naylor</hi> requireth Scripture grounds for what hee aſſerteth, which hee never yet gave.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is I that require Scripture grounds of him for what hee aſſerteth, the which hee hath not yet, nor cannot give; and that maketh him to put it in the quite contrary ſence, as I ſuppoſe, leaſt the ſimple ſhould diſcerne him.</p>
            <p n="23">23. That wee have no faith in God, but in a lying ſpirit within.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It really appeares that ſpirit within them is a lying ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and yet in that they beleeve: but the Spirit of God is not a lying ſpirit, therefore their faith is not in God.</p>
            <p n="24">24. That wee would make the blood of Chriſt of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is true, your doctrine doth ſo, what in your lyeth, as it is prooved in the Treatiſe, and not yet anſwered.</p>
            <p n="25">25. That our ſpirit teacheth us not to put off our hatts when wee pray.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I was ſo informed by thoſe that have ſeene you pray, that your practiſe is ſo, and then I ſuppoſe your ſpirit ſo teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you: ſo that if it be not true, yet it not my lye, becauſe I was ſo informed.</p>
            <p>Thus his twenty-five lyes that hee would father upon mee, I Returne backe to himſelfe in this ſhort dreſſe: And ſhall paſſe over his language hee giveth mee, as grounded hence; becauſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:105464:24"/>it wanteth footing, and come to his laſt maine charge.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, ſaith hee, thou goes on to plead for a deale more of thy Maſters ſtuffe, wherewithall hee houlds up his kingdome, of pride and partialitie, and ſuch like ſtuffe as none ever plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, but the Devill and his Miniſters, who is afraid that his kingdowne ſhould goe downe.</p>
            <p>And thou ſayes Sathan tells us that it is our dutie to obſerve the language held forth in Scripture, and the example of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, and upon paine of damnation not to varie from it: And this thou brings to plead againſt ſpeaking the word (thou) to a particular.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, If it be laid upon us as an injunction, and that upon paine of damnation: And no ſuch injunction to be found in Scripture, it muſt needs be of Sathan.</p>
            <p>But <hi>James Naylor</hi> knoweth there is no ſuch Injunction upon that penaltie in all the Scripture, as to threaten damnation for uſing the cuſtome of the Countrie wherein there is no ſinne, though they varie from the cuſtomes in old time. As ſo If <hi>James Naylor</hi> ſhould tell mee, that in Regard Chriſt wore a coate without ſeame, therefore I may not weare any but ſuch, and that upon paine of damnation: I ſhould alſo ſay, that it came from the Devill, nor doe I thinke that <hi>James</hi> will teach the <hi>Quakers</hi> to follow the example of Chriſt in this thing.</p>
            <p>But hee ſaith, haſt thou been all along crying up Scriptures in thy booke for a Rule, and is now the language of it, and the examples of Chriſt and his Apoſtles therein become a perſwaſion of Sathan with thee; haſt thou not heere ſhewed what broode thou art one, who preferres the Devills pride, and the worlds faſhions, before the examples of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, and would render it a perſwaſion of Sathan for us to follow it, art not thou hee the Apoſtle ſpeakes on, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that if <hi>James Naylor</hi> have any Scripture Rule that bindeth us to it, I will obſerve it, and confeſſe my errour in plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt it: But this Scripture hee bringeth hath nothing in it to this purpoſe, but againſt it, the words are theſe which hee ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, but in part, leaſt it touch himſelfe, to wit,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any man teach otherwiſe, and conſent not to wholeſome words, even the words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to the doctrine which
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105464:24"/>is according to godlineſſe, hee is proud, knowing nothing, but doat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about queſtions and ſtriffes of words, whereof cometh envy, ſtrife, Raylings, evill ſurmiſings, perverſe diſputings of men of corrupt minds, and deſtitute of the truth: ſuppoſing that gaine is godlineſſe, from ſuch withdraw thy ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I know nothing by my ſelfe, but I doe conſent <hi>to the wholeſome words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the doctrine which is according to godlineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is this doctrine according to godlineſſe, to binde us up to the word <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>thou,</hi> becauſe it was the ordinarie language of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; when there is no ſuch obligation in any of their words, and yet they tould us all things <hi>that pertained to life and godlineſſe, and kept backe nothing, but declared even the whole counſaile of God:</hi> ſee <hi>Job</hi> 18.2, 3. for the word <hi>you</hi> to a ſingle perſon. <hi>How long will it be ere you make an end of words? mark, and afterwards we will ſpeak. Wherefore are wee counted as beaſts, and reputed vile in your ſight?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if this were intended, then wee muſt not varie in our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from the words of the Lords prayer, or the prayers of the Apoſtles upon paine of damnation. But carnall men make carnall interpretations: ſuch as <hi>Nicodemus</hi> did, not knowing what it meant to be <hi>borne againe,</hi> unleſſe he ſhould <hi>enter into his mothers wombe</hi> firſt. Nor no more doth <hi>James Naylor</hi> what that doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is which is <hi>according to godlineſſe,</hi> and therefore maketh this carnall uſe of it, which was never intended by the Holy Ghoſt, and therefore it is hee that is <hi>doating about queſtions and ſtriffe of words,</hi> which produce no better fruits, but as the Apoſtle relates, and yet hee is puft up with pride, and triumpheth as if hee had got a great conqueſt.</p>
            <p>But doth <hi>James Naylor</hi> conſent <hi>to the doctrine which is accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to godlineſſe;</hi> why then doth hee make ſuch a carnall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, which was never intended. I ſay it was never intended, let him proove it to the contrary: if hee can let him proove any unwholſomneſſe or ungodlineſſe in uſing the word <hi>(you)</hi> to a ſingle perſon from any Scripture ground, elſe hee but doateth, and befooleth poore ſimple people, and bringeth them into a ſuare without a cauſe.</p>
            <p>I referre the Reader to my booke for further ſatisfaction by reaſon.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:105464:25"/>
            <p> Againe, hee ſaith, thou pleads for bowing unto men, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the hatt, and ſayes the Spirit of God teaches it, wherein thou belyes the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, a very heavie charge if it were true; but the lyar is one of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> who might have quaked to have writt this charge, Conſidering I tould him this curteſie is included under that command, to wit, <hi>Bee yee courteous and tender-hearted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that it were eaſie to proove that bowing of the body was the cuſtomarie Reverence in old time; But I rather asked them what courteſie at all they ſhew to any man upon any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>And that taking off the hart is a proper Reverend duty to thoſe whom wee honour and doe and ought to reverence, is eaſie to proove: And that wee are commanded to <hi>honour all men,</hi> ſo that if wee know them to be dutyes, either of love or honour, wee are bound to uſe them.</p>
            <p>Nay, that if they be proper expreſſions, either of love or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and that wee have any ſpirit of love or honour in us, it will naturally ingage us to uſe ſuch expreſſions one to another, if wee were not ſo commanded.</p>
            <p>Now for bowing of the body, this is cleare from examples; and thoſe unrepeald by the coming of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For as the Apoſtle adviſeth women that profeſſe the feare of God, to follow the examples of <hi>Sarah,</hi> and other holy women; So I thinke I may from the ſame ground adviſe to follow the example of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and other holy men: my ground is from.</p>
            <p>Now it is well knowne, that <hi>before Jacob mett his brother Eſau, hee bowed himſelfe to the ground ſeaven times, untill hee came neare to his brother.</hi> And ſo alſo did <hi>his wives, and children, and maids;</hi> ſee <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</p>
            <p>Now this bowing and calling him Lord was but to his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that <hi>prophane Eſau,</hi> and yet the Spirit of God ingaged him to this humble and courteous demeanour, and to ſuch hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble appellations, calling him <hi>My Lord.</hi> Now this being cordiall, was no honour but ſuch as cometh of God. Nor doe I ſeeke ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther honour from <hi>James Naylor,</hi> nor any other, neither care I for it.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:105464:25"/>
            <p> And therefore I ſaid that by my conſent they ſhall never be perſwaded to uſe them at all, till their cordiall love and reſpects ingage them ſincerely to it; I onely pleaded for the lawfulneſſe and engagement that lay upon us to uſe it, for it is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for them till the ſpirit of love and honour be in them, for they ſhould but deceive us, as ſo I ſaid in my booke.</p>
            <p>And for courteous and honourable and reſpective appellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſee <hi>Luke</hi> the 1.3 to <hi>Theophilus, moſt excellent Theophilus;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Aprippa, Oh King Agrippa;</hi> and to <hi>Feſtus,</hi> though hee thought him to be mad, <hi>Moſt Noble Feſtus:</hi> ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 26.19.25. This was not like that ſpirit in the <hi>Quakers,</hi> by which they were guided.</p>
            <p>And for putting off the hatt when wee expreſſe any courteſie, or honour, or Reverence, either to God or men, it is clearely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of men by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.7. <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he. <hi>a man ought not to cover his head for as much as hee is the Image and glorie of God.</hi> That is to ſay, hee ought not to cover the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie of God, which appeareth in his face, but unvaile his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which is much in ſhew upon any occation, according to the temper of the heart and minde, whether it be tempered with love or anger; love maketh the countenance amiable and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and an honourable Reſpect is much ſeene in the humble feare of the countenance; And ſo is anger and ſcorne on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part, for the temper of a mans ſpirit will appeare in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head and eyes, and can ſcarce be diſſembled.</p>
            <p>And therefore, if there be any love or Reſpect and honour in the heart, it will naturally ingage us to uncover it; neither need wee be aſhamed of it, for ſuch affections are Reall fruits of the Spirit of God, which ought not to be vailed but diſcovered and expreſt, according to the truth and ſinceritie thereof, they being lovely in themſelves, and much inducive to the like Returnes of Reciprocall Communication of love and honour where it is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere; For the looking forth of the ſpirit of love through the eyes and face, is as an invitation to the ſame ſpirit, if it be in another, to looke forth alſo, and ſalute each other, beeing not two but one and the ſame ſpirit, though in two perſons by operation in both their ſpirits, to ſhew its oneneſſe and make them ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if they doe apply, yea <hi>that they may be one as God is one;</hi> for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105464:26"/>nothing but love can make two one, as God is one, and there is no ſpirit of love but one, and that is God; I meane of love that is true and lawfull.</p>
            <p>Now this ſpirit of love is the ſame ſpirit in us which was in the Patriarkes before the Law was given forth, and did ingage them to ſuch humble, honourable, and amiable affections, and to ſuch expreſſions as are naturall to it; And if we have any little mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſame ſpirit, it will ingage us alſo to doe the like, if wee doe not reſiſt it, and wee are forbid to <hi>reſiſt the ſpirit.</hi> Now it ſometimes ingageth thoſe in whom it dwells to lift up their eyes, or their hands towards heaven, and ſometimes both, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as it ingageth the heart and affections, the which if wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt wee reſiſt the ſpirit. And it is eaſily diſcernable through the eyes, whether ſuch their motions come from the heart, or they are but fained, eſpecially by ſuch who are alſo acquainted with ſuch ejaculations of their owne hearts, and of their eyes and hands, as they are affected. And I doe beleeve that many of the <hi>Quakers</hi> have <hi>reſiſted the ſpirit,</hi> and <hi>quenched</hi> it alſo, before they could get their hearts to comply with ſuch uncourteous carriage, as not to put off their hatts, and bow their bodies, and uſe the word <hi>(you)</hi> to ſuch whom they formerly had been ſo accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. So that now they are growne to ſuch hardneſſe of heart and ſearedneſſe of ſpirit, that nothing can be ſeene in them of <hi>naturall affection,</hi> but more <hi>like bruite beaſts, made to be taken and to be deſtroyed;</hi> ſee 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. as was prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied of them in theſe laſt dayes.</p>
            <p>And whereas hee telleth mee that I belye the ſpirit of God, for, ſaith he, the ſpirit of God forbids it, <hi>James</hi> 2. even that which ſetts up pride, and reſpects perſons.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, ſo doe I alſo forbid pride and reſpect of perſons in that ſenſe there meant, and in many other, and I can love and honour the poore that are virtuous, more then the rich, that are either wicked, or not ſo virtuous, nor would I debaſe or depreſſe the poore, becauſe he is poore, to exalt the rich in partiall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. But I muſt <hi>honour all men,</hi> and give them due reſpect, and ſhall I hope as I know what it is: but to ſhew no reſpect to any at all, as ſo the <hi>Quakers</hi> doe, is to ſhew plainly, that I have not any love or Reſpect in mee.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:105464:26"/>
            <p> And againe ſaith hee, Chriſt himſelfe ſaith, <hi>How can you beleeve that Receive honour one of another,</hi> John 5.44. And if they could not beleeve that received honour, how much leſſe can you beleeve that ſeeke it and grudge if you have it not.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, let them that ſeeke it or Receive it either, that which cometh but from men anſwer for themſelves; I ſeeke it not, nor receive it neither, but <hi>that which cometh of God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> if I know it from the other: Now <hi>that which cometh of God</hi> is really cordiall, and I muſt receive it, and Returne the like, as ſo I am naturally ingaged by the love and honour which is of God in my owne ſoule; nor doe I diſſemble any more then they.</p>
            <p>Now there is a common love, and a common reſpect and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomarie honour, to which I am bound by that command, to wit, <hi>honour all men,</hi> but there is a nearer and more particular love, and honour, and courteſie, which will induce mee to a fuller expreſſion, both in word and deed, and I am ſo inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the ſame ſpirit, and in all this there is no partiallitie, or reſpect of perſons, but as I ought to doe; And ſo his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of mee to <hi>Haman,</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> I have good ground to deny.</p>
            <p>And againe, ſaith hee, not having any Scripture to plead for theſe things, thou wouldſt plead for them under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>love,</hi> and being <hi>courteous, and tender-hearted.</hi> I ſay, ſaith he, ſilence deceite, you have ſett up theſe things, till you have loſt all love but what is ſelfiſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, I did produce diverſe Scriptures, but they are none it ſeemes, with him; is there no Scripture that commandeth <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>to be courteous, and tender-hearted?</hi> What ſpirit is this but a lying Devill, that proceedeth on upon this lying founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to rayling and reviling, and propheſying the deſtruction of all our fading glorie, becauſe wee maintaine the lawfullneſſe of theſe cuſtomarie Civilities, but becauſe his bookes are ſo full of lyes. I doe not much regard either his rayling or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying, but to cleare up the truth: which the Lord aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mee, I have in ſome meaſure done; and doe commit
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:105464:27"/>the ſame to his bleſſing, and diſpoſall, to whom be all the honour, and glorie, and praiſe, for ever and ever, Amen, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:105464:27"/>
            <head>A Poſtſcript to fill up a ſheet that wanted,</head>
            <argument>
               <p>being a Catalogue of ſome of <hi>James Naylors</hi> lyes, gathered out of his booke in five or ſix houres time, to let the Reader ſee hee is none of thoſe <hi>children that will not lye;</hi> but when hee can no otherwiſe ſhift off the dint of a Scripture, or argument, hee maketh <hi>lyes his Refuge,</hi> and under <hi>vanitie would hide himſelfe,</hi> if ſuch coverings were not too narrow, but that hee could <hi>wrapp himſelfe.</hi> How faine would hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be all in ſheepes cloathing, though Inwardly hee is ravening and Woolffiſh.</p>
            </argument>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>A Catalogue of ſome of</hi> James Naylors <hi>lyes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. HEE ſaith, my booke is much boaſted off by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, but as little worth as the boaſt is great.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hee ſaith, it was my envie that carried me with ſuch envie againſt the Innocent, till I ſpake I knew not what.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hee ſaith, hee hath ſet downe ſome markes and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the true Miniſters; and alſo of the falſe, their fruits dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering them according to Chriſts Rules in Scripture; with diverſe other things to keepe the ſimple from deceit.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hee ſaith, it is by a friend to the worke of God, but an enemy to the Devills worke, where it is found and pleaded for, called by the world <hi>James Naylor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe foure lyes are in his Title page, and are anſwered, <hi>pag.</hi> 1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Hee ſaith, I have boaſted much of my worke.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That I have forgot that teaching, to let other men praiſe mee, and not my owne mouth.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That I have prooved nothing againſt <hi>James Naylor,</hi> but againſt my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Theſe three are in his firſt page.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That I have writ againſt the light of Chriſt being ſufficient.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:105464:28"/> 9. That I would binde them to creature-worſhips, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall cuſtomes.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That I ſhould blame him for producing that Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That I bring not one Scripture that ſaith the letter is the word.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That I ſet my ſelfe in the ſtead of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe laſt five are in <hi>pag.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Hee calleth mee an exalted wretch.</p>
            <p n="14">14. That I confound my ſelfe in what I would diſproove the truth; theſe <hi>pag.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p n="15">15. That hee denyed but that the Scriptures given by Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God, are words of God.</p>
            <p n="16">16. That the <hi>Jewes</hi> had all the Scripture in their hand, or in their braine, and yet had not the word.</p>
            <p n="17">17. That I deny the letter it ſelfe, and the letter denyes mee.</p>
            <p n="18">18. That I bring thoſe Scriptures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. to wit, the Law is ſpirituall; and <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.1. to oppoſe the new Covenant, and the Law in the heart; theſe <hi>pag.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p n="19">19. That all the Scriptures I bring, turne againſt mee, and for the truth.</p>
            <p n="20">20. That I ſteale Scripture words out of Scripture, to plead for pride, and vaine-glory, and creature worſhips, and an Idoll Miniſtrie, contrary to Scripture, ſet up in will and inventions of men, in my booke; theſe <hi>pag.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p n="21">21. That of the words of God there is a famine, and greateſt amongſt ſuch as trade with the letter.</p>
            <p n="22">22. That I increaſe in miſchiefe, and know not the plant of Gods renowne how it growes, nor what the increaſe of God is.</p>
            <p n="23">23. That they know what it is to grow in Chriſt, and that Chriſt is in them; theſe <hi>pag.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p n="24">24. That I bring Scriptures to proove the light of Chriſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient; <hi>pag.</hi> 8.</p>
            <p n="25">25. That mine eye was ſo much abroad to diſcover errours in <hi>James Naylor,</hi> till I could not ſee mine owne.</p>
            <p n="26">26. That I have drunke deeply of the Cup full of abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and errours from the mother of confuſions.</p>
            <p n="27">27. That the meanes I am pleading for is come through ſo
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:105464:28"/>many ſeverall hands, till it have loſt both life and power; theſe <hi>pag.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p n="28">28. That I love mine iniquities, and am pleading for them, pride, Imperfection, and fulſe worſhips; <hi>pag.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p n="29">29. That I am hee who turnes the Scriptures as a noſe of wax, to plead for ſuch things as the Scripture condemnes.</p>
            <p n="30">30. That as a meanes to turne people to that light within <hi>James Naylor</hi> is.</p>
            <p n="31">31. That I am one of thoſe people that are of no under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, therefore hee that made mee will have no mercy on mee.</p>
            <p n="32">32. That I have got the Serpents ſubtiltie, to thruſt in my words to abuſe the Scriptures, <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p n="33">33. That I ſhall one day know that I have blaſphemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpirit and gift of God; <hi>pag.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p n="34">34. That now wee have got a little peace, wee are turning backe to <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="35">35. That wee pleade againſt the Spirit; <hi>pag.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p n="36">36. That I am hee who am leading forth from the kingdome of God within.</p>
            <p n="37">37. That the <hi>Ranters</hi> are my brethren, all of one kingdome in the fleſh, and the luſts thereof; <hi>pag.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p n="38">38. That by reviling the workes of Righteouſneſſe and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Spirit, and ſpirituall light, I have made it odious for any man to follow, as the Devill himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="39">39. That my third thing is for my maintenance, and for my Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="40">40. That I put in the poore with the Miniſters, that I might ſeeme charitable, like as <hi>Judas</hi> did; <hi>pag.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p n="41">41. That I have ſett a ſtint for Miniſters maintenance, and for the poore, though before I denyed it; <hi>pag.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p n="42">42. That accounting ſuch ſpirituall fathers, who have not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten us, is to account of a lye, and that I teach them to it; <hi>pag.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p n="43">43. That my booke hath a heape of confuſion in it fitt for the fire.</p>
            <p n="44">44. That I preferre the Devills pride, and the worlds faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, before the example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p n="45">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:105464:29"/> 45. That ſuch as I preferre the words of pride, before the words of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="46">46. That I belye the Spirit of God for the Spirit of God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids bowing unto men, and putting off the hatt.</p>
            <p n="47">47. That wee ſeeke honour of men, and grudge if wee have it not.</p>
            <p n="48">48. That the demeanour of Chriſt and his Saints is become a Reproach, and not manners and courteſie to give us content.</p>
            <p n="49">49. That wee are ſeeking for that honour which God is lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the duſt.</p>
            <p n="50">50. That there is much more ſuch ſtuffe in my booke, not worth reading, nor anſwering, which riſes out of the corruption of mine owne heart and buſie minde, and that <hi>Iſhmaell</hi>-like my hand is againſt every man, and eyes abroad, but cannot ſee mine owne folly, but am boaſting of it; <hi>pag.</hi> 27.</p>
            <p n="51">51. That wee have found out ſo many words in our inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſo many lights, and all without us, that wee are become heart-blinde.</p>
            <p n="52">52. That the Lord God and the Lambe will they worſhip for ever.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
